<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The perfection of military discipline after the newest method, as practised in England and Ireland, &amp;c., or, The industrious souldiers golden treasury of knowledge in the art of making war containing instructions for the exercising the pike and musket in all their postures, with the signs of the drum, by its beating the several points of war, the exercise of granadeers, horse, and dragoons : the explanation of the words of command, and how to be put in practice ... : the several doublings, wheelings, and drawing up of battalions, squadrons of horse, &amp;c. with the conduct of armies in open or inclosed countries, or upon any occasion or immergency ... the method to be observed in garrisons, and the manner of fortification, with that of besieging strong holds, &amp;c. to which is added, as a second part, The art of gunnery, or, The compleat engineer : shewing the practice of the ordnance, mortars, &amp;c. with the manner of making and using fire-works for war, at sea and land, and many other things necessary to be known for the improvement of souldiers.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1690</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 191 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 82 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A54357</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P1532</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R18339</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12602441</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12602441</idno>
            <idno type="VID">64196</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A54357)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 64196)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 771:21)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The perfection of military discipline after the newest method, as practised in England and Ireland, &amp;c., or, The industrious souldiers golden treasury of knowledge in the art of making war containing instructions for the exercising the pike and musket in all their postures, with the signs of the drum, by its beating the several points of war, the exercise of granadeers, horse, and dragoons : the explanation of the words of command, and how to be put in practice ... : the several doublings, wheelings, and drawing up of battalions, squadrons of horse, &amp;c. with the conduct of armies in open or inclosed countries, or upon any occasion or immergency ... the method to be observed in garrisons, and the manner of fortification, with that of besieging strong holds, &amp;c. to which is added, as a second part, The art of gunnery, or, The compleat engineer : shewing the practice of the ordnance, mortars, &amp;c. with the manner of making and using fire-works for war, at sea and land, and many other things necessary to be known for the improvement of souldiers.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 156 p., 1 leaf of folded plates.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Nicholas Boddington ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1690.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Gunnery.</term>
               <term>Military art and science --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02</date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02</date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:64196:1"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>man on a horse</figDesc>
                  <head>
                     <l>Behold A Prince Renownd In Peace and Arms.</l>
                     <l>whos name and Fame the world with wonder Charms. </l>
                     <l>The Be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>gian Glory and Great Britains Joy. </l>
                     <l>who saued the Dear Palladium of our Troy.</l>
                  </head>
                  <byline>P. P. Beu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ho Soul:</byline>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:64196:1"/>
            <p>The Perfection of Military Diſcipline After the Neweſt Method, As Practiſed In <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> &amp;c. OR, The Induſtrious SOULDIERS <hi>Golden Treaſury</hi> of Knowledge in the Art of making WAR.</p>
            <p>CONTAINING, Inſtructions for the Exerciſing the Pike and Musket in all their Poſtures, with the Signs of the Drum, by its beating the ſeveral Points of War, the Exerciſe of Granadeers, Horſe, and Dragoons: The Explana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Words of Command, and how to be put in Practice: The manner of drawing up in ſeveral forms of Battle: The various Fireings and Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages to be gained thereby: The ſeveral Doublings, Wheelings, and drawing up of Battalions, Squa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drons of Horſe, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> with the conduct of Armies in open or incloſed Countries, or upon any occaſion or Immergency: How the detached Party and Officers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ought to carry themſelves; ſeveral ways off of Incampment, opening difficult Paſſes, taking Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, paſſing Bridges, oppoſing Towns, or For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treſſes. The Method to be obſerved in Garriſons, and the manner of Fortification, with that of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieging ſtrong Holds, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>To which is added, as a Second Part.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Art of Gunnery,</hi> or the <hi>Compleat Engineer,</hi> ſhewing the Practice of the Ordnance, Mortars, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> with the manner of making and uſing Fire-works for War, at Sea and Land, and many other things neceſſary to be known for the Improvement of Souldiers.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London:</hi> Printed for <hi>Nicholas Boddington,</hi> at the <hi>Golden Ball</hi> in <hi>Duck-Lane,</hi> 1690.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:64196:2"/>
            <p>Liſenced according to Order.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Octob.</hi> 12. 1689.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:64196:2"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <p>THE Profeſſion of Arms has in all Ages been in ſuch Eſteem, that the Great Men of the World have made it their Study; Emperours and Kings have preferred the Name of a Souldier above the reſt of their Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Titles, and indeed, the Sword is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly the Bullwark of a Kingdom, without which the Laws would prove weak and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>effectual; for did not the Violaters fear that Power, which is of force to compel them to undergoe the Penalties of the Laws, they would eſteem them but a dead Letter: And to ſpeak more plain, The Souldier is the Guard of Liberty, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty, and what ever is dear to Mankind, as being at all times ready to ſacrifice his Life for the Defence of his Country; nor are the Advantages ſmall that may incite men to the ſtudy of the <hi>Military Art,</hi> for it is often ſeen, that Perſons of mean Birth
<pb facs="tcp:64196:3"/> and Fortune, have by their Courage and Induſtry become great Commanders; and many times Generals of Armies: Courage indeed, is a great Qualification in the profeſſion of Arms, but without Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence it frequently does hurt, and rarely raiſes a man to any conſiderable Station; but joyned with Experience, and kept with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in bounds, it wants but Opportunity to make him Eminent, though many Books of this kind have appeared in the World, yet being either of an extraordinary Price, or wanting ſomewhat new, and neceſſary to be known, we thought fit, eſpecially for the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of young Souldiers, to compile in a ſmall Volume ſuch a Body of <hi>Military Diſciplin'd,</hi> &amp;c. as at this time is Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctical, and approved by the great Captains of the Age, that they may be able to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand their Duty, and perform it with Exactneſs and Dexterity; ſo that being well grounded in the moſt neceſſary and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Art, their Courage, Zeal, and Loyalty, may not only fruſtrate the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of our Enemies abroad, and at home, but render theſe Kingdoms Dreadful to our Neighbours, and Happy in themſelves.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="part">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:64196:3"/>
            <head>The Perfection of <hi>MILITARY DISCIPLINE</hi> After the Neweſt Method, As Practiſed In <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <p>THE moſt promiſing things to Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferment in this great Art, are Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour and Obedience, for it is not only very commendable when occaſion offers to fight Valiantly, but likewiſe to obey Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiently, the latter being looked upon as a great Vertue; to theſe Experience acquired by Labour, and Induſtry being joyned, Difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties will the eaſier be overcome; a man may indeed, a long time bare Arms, and yet be ignorant in many things he ought materially to know; but an Induſtrious Mind will ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſh much in a ſhort time.</p>
            <p>There are ſeveral things in the <hi>Military Art</hi> to be conſidered, and in the firſt place, thoſe properly called the Senſes, by which we receive Advertiſement, as the Eye and
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:64196:4"/> the Ear; and in this caſe a ſtrict Obſervance, and Silence is required, that the one and the other may not be miſtaken. The Signes uſed in War, are commonly three, <hi>viz. The Voice which conveys the word of Command to the Ear. The Trumpet or Drum which by certain Sounds and Beats give notice to the Cavalry and Infan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try what is to be done.</hi> And the laſt is, <hi>The Hand Colours, or other Signs which inform the Eye;</hi> and theſe are called <hi>Vocal Semi-vocal</hi> and <hi>Mute,</hi> and theſe muſt be perfectly under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, or elſe by miſtake, or not knowing what to do, a Souldier may run into great Error, eſpecially in Battle, looſing himſelf, and being the occaſion of the loſs others: But of this more hereafter.</p>
            <p>When it happens that a Regiment has the word of Command to draw out, then ought the Major, or Adjutant, to Aſſign each Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany its proper Poſt, and this muſt be done by placing the eldeſt Company upon the Right, and the next to that on the Left, and ſo in order to the youngeſt, who by this meanes will come into the Center, and every Company or Body of Men are to be drawn up in the beginning at the ſame order they march at, as well in Rank, as File, the ſingle Companies always taking notice to leave ſo much room as the Serjeants and Drums may place themſelves in, on the Right and Left of each Company: Then obſerve before you
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:64196:4"/> form your Battalions, to draw up from every Company the odd Men, forming in Oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition a Rank at fifty paces in diſtance from the head of each Company, that no broken Files may appear; and by this means with more ſpeed and dexterity you may compleat the Files.</p>
            <p>The Battalions may be form'd, the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies diſpoſed in order as aforeſaid by theſe words of Command, <hi>viz.</hi> 1. <hi>Have a care to form the Battalion.</hi> 2. <hi>Muſqueteers, to the Right and Left outwards.</hi> 3. <hi>Pikes, to the Right and Left inwards.</hi> 4. <hi>March inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changing Ground.</hi> Upon the interchange of Ground by the Pikes and Muſqueteers; the firſt Rank of Pikes muſt paſs before the firſt Rank of Muſqueteers: And it ever is to be noted, That after Command for moving of any kind, no man ſtir till the word <hi>March</hi> be uttered, ſo that they may move joyntly, and not break the Order.</p>
            <p>The Ground being changed, the Souldiers muſt forbear to face to their Leaders till they be ſo commanded, which done, they are in Battalia at cloſe Order in File; and the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers in this caſe muſt have a regard to the whole, as not limitted to their particular Companies, and the Commandant muſt take notice how many Serjeants are preſent, and if the Battalian contain eight or ten Companies, or a bigger number, and every Company two
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:64196:5"/> Serjeants, and three Corporals deſigned to do the duty of Serjeants, two muſt neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily be placed on each Rank, to the Right and Left, and the others muſt have their Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in the Rear; but if the Serjeants be not ſo many, then there will be allowed but one to each Rank, to the Right and Left, and the reſt in the Rear, making a Parallel Rank to the Souldiers, keeping three paces diſtance from the Rank.</p>
            <p>The Serjeants thus placed, the Drums muſt ſtand one half on the Right, and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther half on the Left, that they may range directly with the firſt Rank of the Souldiers; but if the Drums be more than uſual, and the ground be ſtreight, then they may be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed in two Ranks, on the Right and Left, ranging with the two firſt Ranks of Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers ever ſlinging their Drums, unleſs con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary Command be given. The <hi>Hoitboys,</hi> if there be any, are to take the right of the Drums which are on the right of the Batta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion ranging with them in the ſame Ranks.</p>
            <p>The Commiſſion Officers, according to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Military Diſcipline, are to take their places at the head of the Battalion, as the Colours are drawn; but more of this hereafter. In this cloſe Order, the Ranks, by the care of the Serjeants, are to have twelve large Feet diſtance between Rank and Rank, which muſt be kept very even, the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:64196:5"/> Chief Commandant to place himſelf about forty paces diſtant from the Center of the Pikes.</p>
            <p>As to the words of Command, they muſt be given with deliberation, leaſt command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing too faſt put the Souldiers beſide their Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe; Silence being commanded, the next word of Command is,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Files, open to the Right</hi> (or to the Left) <hi>to your Order. March.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>At theſe words each Souldier turns to the hand mentioned, and after a ſhort ſtand the Flanking Searjeants lead the Ranks (which by this means are Files) marching ſlowly for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward by ſhort ſteps; the Serjeants with ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced Halberts, the Iron uppermoſt: every man, if they move to the Right, obſerving the left-hand man, if to the Left, the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, and as ſoon as the laſt man but one of the firſt Rank ſtirs, the Command is to be given for them all to <hi>Halt.</hi> And in proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to open Files after this manner, no man ought to move till his Leader be at four foot diſtance, and then to move with equal pace and keep the diſtance, ſo that when faced to the proper Front, there will be three foot ſpace between them: The word of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand to <hi>Halt</hi> being given; the word of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand ſucceeding is,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>To your Leader.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:64196:6"/>
            <p>In this caſe the Captains and Lieutenants are to carry their Pikes comported ever when they move to the Right, or Left; the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns being Advanced, the Ranks muſt alſo be kept even at twelve feet diſtance, which is the Serjeants Care, the Files muſt be likewiſe at three feet diſtance, each having regard to his right and left-hand man.</p>
            <p>To draw the Officers from the Front of the Battalion to the Rear; theſe words muſt be uſed, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Have a care of the Exerciſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Upon this the Muſqueteers are to draw off their right-hand Gloves; and ſtick them in their Girdles. The next words are, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Officers take your Poſts of Exerciſe in the Rear. March.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Upon this the Officers muſt face to the right-about, the Captains marching a pretty ſwift pace in the one Rank, and the Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants and Colours in another, two paces be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind; Captains and Lieutenants, carrying their Pikes Advanced; being in the Rear, the Lieutenants and Enſigns are to take their places in a Rank about twelve feet from the Serjeants; the Captains ought to be thirteen paces from the laſt Rank of Souldiers, and the Lieutenants and Colours eleven; and at this word of Command, or further ſignal from the Officers to take their Poſts of Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe in the Rear, ſix Serjeants of the Rear
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:64196:6"/> muſt march thorough the Intervals of the Files, poſting themſelves in the Front forty ſix paces from the firſt Rank of Souldiers, being advanced ſix paces before the Chief Commandant, making by their ranging, a parallel Line with the Battalion, keeping the Front free, and undiſordered. This word being likewiſe given, the Pike men muſt joyn their left-hands with their Pikes, placing them even with their Shoulder.</p>
            <p>We ſuppoſe the Muſqueteers to have Shoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, and the Pikes Advanced, none are to ſpeak after Silence is Commanded, but the Officer in Chief who thus proceeds,</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Order your Pikes.</hi> 2. <hi>To the Right, to the Right, to the Right, to the Right, to the Right-about, as you were; To the Left, to the Left, to the Left, to the Left, to the Left-about, as you were.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Words of Command for the Exerciſe of the <hi>Fire-Lock</hi> and <hi>Pike.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="1">
                  <hi>1.</hi> MVsqueteers, have a care of the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe, and carry your Arms well. <hi>2.</hi> Lay your right hands on your Muskets. <hi>3.</hi> Poiſe your Muskets. <hi>4.</hi> Reſt your Mus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kets. <hi>5.</hi> Cock your Muskets. <hi>6.</hi> Guard
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:64196:7"/> your Musket. <hi>7.</hi> Preſent. <hi>8.</hi> Fire. <hi>9.</hi> Recover your Arms. <hi>10.</hi> Half bend your Muskets. <hi>11.</hi> Clean your Pans. <hi>12.</hi> Handle your Primers. <hi>13.</hi> Prime. <hi>14.</hi> Shut your Pans. <hi>15.</hi> Blow off your looſe Corns. <hi>16.</hi> Caſt about to Charge. <hi>17.</hi> Handle your Chargers. <hi>18.</hi> Open them with your Teeth. <hi>19.</hi> Charge with Powder. <hi>20.</hi> Draw forth your Scowerers. <hi>21.</hi> Shorten them to an Inch. <hi>22.</hi> Charge with Bullet. <hi>23.</hi> Ram down Powder and Ball. <hi>24.</hi> Withdraw your Scowerers. <hi>25.</hi> Shorten them to a Handfull. <hi>26.</hi> Return your Scowerers. <hi>27.</hi> Poiſe your Muskets. <hi>28.</hi> Shoulder. your Muskets. <hi>29.</hi> Order your Musket. <hi>30.</hi> Pike-men, take heed. <hi>31.</hi> Advance your Pikes, to the Front, Charge. <hi>32.</hi> To the Right, Charge. <hi>33.</hi> To the Right, Charge. <hi>34.</hi> To the Right, Charge. <hi>35.</hi> To the Right, Charge. <hi>36.</hi> To the Right-about, Charge. <hi>37.</hi> As you were, Charge. <hi>38.</hi> To the Left, Charge, <hi>39.</hi> To the Left, Charge. <hi>40.</hi> To the Left, Charge. <hi>41.</hi> To the Left, Charge. <hi>42.</hi> To the Left-about, Charge. <hi>43.</hi> As you were, Charge. <hi>44.</hi> Advance your Pikes. <hi>45.</hi> Shoulder your Pikes. <hi>46.</hi> Charge to the Front, <hi>47.</hi> As you were, Charge to the Right, as you were. <hi>84.</hi> Charge to the Right-about. <hi>49.</hi> As you were, Charge to the Left, as you were. <hi>50.</hi> Charge to the Left-about. <hi>51.</hi> As you were.
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:64196:7"/> 
                  <hi>52.</hi> Port. <hi>53.</hi> Comport. <hi>54.</hi> Charge to the Front. <hi>55</hi> Trail your Pike. <hi>56.</hi> Charge as you were. <hi>57.</hi> Advance your Pikes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>When you Exerciſe thus, it muſt be done altogether, and not one after another, that a whole Battalion may ſeem to do but one and the ſame Action. Then to proceed further, <hi>viz.</hi>
                  </hi> Musqueteers take heed. Poiſe your Muskets. Shoulder your Muskets. Muſque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teers, make Ready; <hi>at which time all the Poſtures of the Musket are to be performed by the Muſqueteers together, which readineſs imploys a Cocking, which muſt be guarded with the Thumb, leaſt it ſhould go off unſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonably, and the Muskets brought ſtreight before them, with the left hands a little a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove the Chin. The Pike-men at the word,</hi> Make Ready, <hi>are likewiſe to bear their Pikes ſtraight before them, and recover their left hands the height of their Ears, both of them obſerving when they come to this Poſture, to recover their Arms before them, that they bring their right Heels to their left Inſteps; and when the Pikes Charge, and the Muſque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teers reſt, to retire, or fall back with the right Feet in a direct Line, obſerving in all Charg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, or Motions of the Pikes or Muskets, to take care that they clatter not one againſt another.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:64196:8"/>
               <head>An Explanation of the Words of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand or Poſtures, in Exerciſing the <hi>Fire-Lock, Musket,</hi> and how they muſt be performed.</head>
               <p>WHen you enter upon Exerciſe, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be of Pike or Musket, you muſt obſerve to keep your at Feet a moderate diſtance, that you may upon occaſion retain your full Force and Strength, ever keeping the left Heel firm, and ſet the right Feet: But as to the Exerciſe.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Lay your right Hand on your Musket.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In this Action the Lock being uppermoſt, turn your Barrel towards you, and your Fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers being extended, lay your right Hand juſt behind the Lock, then cloſe the butt end of your Musket to your Shoulder, ſo that it may in all parts be of an equal height.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Poiſe your Musket.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Here you muſt hold your Musket with a hard graſp, facing to the Right, and turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with a quick motion upon your left Heel, keeping your Musket exactly before you, the height of it between your Shoulders, your right Elbow on your ſide, and your Feet at a moderate diſtance, that turning about, the point of your left Toe may be to the Front, and that of your right, as you face to the left
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:64196:8"/> Heel, being directly againſt the middle your right Foot; and ſo are you in a reſting Poſture, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Reſt your Musket.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In performing this, let your Musket ſlide, or ſink down to your left hand, letting down your Arm as low as poſſible, without ſtoop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, receiving the Musket directly where the Scowerer enters into the Stock, ſuffering your hand to touch no part of the Barrel; let it be a little ſtooping from perpendicular about half a foot from your ſide, keeping your right hand with your fingers extended behind the Lock.</p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>Cock your Musket.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In this doing, place the Thumb of your right Hand and your Finger behind the Trig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and clapping it againſt your Thigh, Cock, keeping for the better ſecurity your Thumb upon the Cock.</p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>Guard your Musket.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In Guarding your Musket, bring it in the foregoing Poſture with a very quick motion ſtraight before you to the Recover, your left hand equal with your Mouth but a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout half a foot diſtance, not ſtooping, nor ſuffering your Musket to ſink, obſerving in bringing up the Musket, before which is a Recovering, to make the right Heel come to the left Inſtep, keeping your Musket right perpendicular.</p>
               <p n="6">
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:64196:9"/>6. <hi>Preſent.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In this caſe, fall back with your right Leg, ſo that the left Heel be againſt the middle of the right Foot, ſuffering the butt end to riſe to you Shoulder, ſetting it faſt, your right Elbow even with the height of the Piece, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ever ready to pull the Trigger with the fourth Finger of your right Hand, bending the left Knee a little, and keeping the right very ſteady, levelling breaſt high.</p>
               <p n="7">7. <hi>Fire.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Here you muſt keep true motion in draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Trigger, doing it all together, ſo that the Fire of a Battalion may give but one Report, or appear to be no more than one Flaſh, the body ſteady, and the Musket cloſe to the Shoulder till the next word of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, which is,</p>
               <p n="8">8. <hi>Recover your Arms.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Hereupon ſuffer the butt end of your Mus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket to ſink in both hands, till it be perpendi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, the right under the Cock, and the left as high as your Mouth always upon a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery, bringing it up before you upon a very quick motion, turning the right Heel, ſo that it may come up with the left In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtep.</p>
               <p n="9">9. <hi>Half bend your Musket.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>With your right Leg fall back, let the Muskets reſt at once, the right Thumbs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon their Cocks, and the right Fingers
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:64196:9"/> behind their Triggers, then cloſing to the Thighs half bend, with your right hands placed behind the Lock, keeping them reſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with fingers extended.</p>
               <p n="10">10. <hi>Clean your Pan.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This you may do by preſſing the ball of your Thumb into the Pan, holding the right hand behind the Lock, that the poſture may the better appear.</p>
               <p n="11">11. <hi>Handle your Primer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In doing this, take the little end between your Thumb and Finger, turning the great end to the back of your Hand, your Arm bearing backward.</p>
               <p n="12">12. <hi>Prime.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Upon priming, level your Piece exactly upon a Line, and having Powder a little bruiſed, ſtrike it into the Pan as much as is convenient, the left Toe being kept upon the Front.</p>
               <p n="13">13. <hi>Shut your Pan.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Here uſe your two firſt Fingers, caſting your Primer back, and drawing up your right Heel to your left Inſtep, your Musket ſtreight up before you Recover, with the Barrel to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards you, done with a quick Motion, the Thumb of your right hand on the top of the Steel, and the left hand as high as your Mouth.</p>
               <p n="14">
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:64196:10"/>14. <hi>Blow off your looſe Corns.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In this caſe, bring your Pan within four Inches of your Mouth, and blow with a ſtrong blaſt, obſerving to do it altogether, ſtanding upright without declining the Head, caſting out your Arms, and ſuffering your Piece to ſink from the poſture it before was in.</p>
               <p n="15">15. <hi>Caſt about to Charge.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In doing this, let your right Leg advance, turning the Barrel of your Musket down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, bringing it to your left ſide ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what backward in your left hand, ſuffering none of your fingers to touch the Barrel, the Toe of the right Foot being directly to the Front, the right Heel over againſt the middle of the left Foot, the Musket ballanced in the left Hand, the Muzle to a proper Front of an equal height, half a foot from your Body, your right hand joyned to the Muzle of the Musket, and your Thumb extended to the ſlde of the Barrel.</p>
               <p n="16">16. <hi>Handle your Charger.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This muſt be done with a full gripe, hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it even with the Muzle of the Musket un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneath about an Inch from it.</p>
               <p n="17">17. <hi>Open it with your Teeth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Here bring it up to your Mouth without bowing your head, then bring the Charger within an Inch of your Muzle underneath, covering the Chargers Mouth with the ball of your Thumb.</p>
               <p n="18">
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:64196:10"/>18. <hi>Charge with Powder.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Having put the Powder with a quick mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion into the Barrel, hold the Charger un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneath, as before.</p>
               <p n="19">19. <hi>Draw forth your Scowerer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Upon this word, let fall your Charger, and by turning your hand, draw your Scow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erer or Gun-ſtick at three motions, holding it level the height of your Forehead, your Arm extended, as if you were about to dart it.</p>
               <p n="20">20. <hi>Shorten it to an Inch.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In this caſe, turning the great end of your Scowerer towards you, let it ſink till within an Inch of the end, reſting it againſt your Body ſome-what below your right Breaſt, ſtooping.</p>
               <p n="21">21. <hi>Charge with Bullet.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Having a Bullet in your Mouth, take it out with your right hand, and put it into the Barrel, placing the great end of your Scow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erer juſt at the Muzle of your Musket.</p>
               <p n="22">22. <hi>Ram down Powder and Ball.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take a full graſp with your Thumb and Fore-finger, from the Muzle your Thumb on the top of the Scowerer, keeping a handful in your hand.</p>
               <p n="23">23. <hi>Withdraw your Scowerer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Your hand Thumb and Fore-finger being turned towards the Muzle, clear your Scow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erer at three motions, and dart it as before.</p>
               <p n="24">
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:64196:11"/>24. <hi>Shorten it to a Handful.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Clap the ſmall end of your Scowerer to your Breaſt, ſlip it to a Handful of the end, holding it a little below your right Breaſt ſlooping.</p>
               <p n="25">25. <hi>Return your Scowerer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Upon this, place it in its proper place, without expecting any word, graſp the Muzle of your Musket with the right hand, your Thumb being extended upon the Scow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erer, keeping it half a foot clear from your Side, the Muzles directly to front all of a height.</p>
               <p n="26">26. <hi>Poiſe your Musket.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In this caſe, with your left hand before you, bring up your Musket, graſp it with your right hand under the Cock, falling with your right Leg to your left, keeping it Poiſed directly before your Noſe, being fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to the Front, let your right Elbow reſt upon your Body.</p>
               <p n="27">27. <hi>Shoulder your Muskets.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In doing this, take the rule that has been mentioned.</p>
               <p n="28">28. <hi>Poiſe your Muskets.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Do this as before has been ſhew'd.</p>
               <p n="29">29. <hi>Order your Muskets.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In doing this, ſink your right hand a little, take hold of the Stock with the left hand on the top of the Scowerer; then ſuffering the left to ſink, take hold of the Muzle with
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:64196:11"/> the right hand, the butt end eaſily ſinking near the ground, when after a little pauſe, let them all come down together, giving as it were but one thump, then cloſe to the right foot place the butt end about the middle of it, the Lock outward, and your right hand an Inch below the Muzle.</p>
               <p n="30">30. <hi>Lay down your Musket.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Having turn'd it with the back upwards, you ſtep forwards with your left Leg, and your right hand lay it on the ground, that it may lie in a ſtreight Line with the reſt, never laying it down with any other but the right hand.</p>
               <p n="31">31. <hi>Quit your Musket.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Stand upright, by raiſing your ſelf with a fall back of your left Leg to your right.</p>
               <p n="32">32. <hi>Handle your Musket.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Here obſerve to ſtep forward with your left Leg, and lay your righ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> hand on the Muzle of your Musket.</p>
               <p n="33">33. <hi>Order your Musket.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Upon this word, raiſe the Muzle, and fall back with your left Leg to your right, turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Lock outwards by the middle of your foot: And thus, in caſe of Fire-Arms, the poſtures are little different, as will hereafter appear.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:64196:12"/>
               <head>Inſtructions for Exerciſing the <hi>Pike,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating to the various Poſtures already mentioned in Command.</head>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Pike-men, take heed. Advance your Pikes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>IN this caſe, move your Pike upward in a direct Line, with your right hand near your ſide, your right hand well near as high as you can reach, depreſſing your left hand as low as you can, your fingers ſtreight out, and raiſe your Pike till the butt end comes to your right hand, at what time, place it between your Breaſt and Shoulder, keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing your butt end cloſe, that it may be more firmly uprigh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>To the Front.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Place your left hand on your Pike even with the top of your Shoulder, caſting your finger ſtreight, bringing your Pike right before you with a very ſwift motion, drawing in your right Heel to your left Inſtep, keeping the Pike ſtreight.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Charge.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In this poſture fall back with your right Leg, ſuffering the heel of your left foot to be againſt the middle of your right, and bring down your Pike with a quick jerk, ſupport
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:64196:12"/> your Pike with your left elbow, and Charge breaſt high, bending your left Knee upon yeilding your Body forward to fix your ſelf the firmer, holding the butt end in the palm of your right hand, your left Toe directly pointing with the ſpear of your Pike, ſet your Feet at a moderate diſtance, to ſtand the more firm, and bring your Pike down a little beneath your breaſt, beware of clatter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, cloſe it to your breaſt when it is Charg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>
                     <hi>To the Right,</hi> four times.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In this doing, turn your left Toe to the right, then make your left Heel come up with your left Inſtep with a quick motion, recovering your Pike ſtraight before you, then having turned, fall back with your right Leg, <hi>Charge,</hi> as before, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>To the Right-about.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Here you muſt, by turning your left Toe, bring it to the Right-about, bringing up your right Heel, your Pike recovered, then Charge being turned with much quickneſs.</p>
               <p n="6">6. <hi>As you were.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Bring up your left Toe by turning to the Left about, then bringing your Pike recovered, your left hand muſt never be higher than your Mouth, your Feet in Order, when being turn'd, you muſt fall back with your right Leg and Charge, bringing your Pike ſtraight up without Clattering.</p>
               <list>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:64196:13"/>
                  <head>Do theſe as has been ſhewn in caſe of the Right, only obſerving 8 left Motions. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <item>7. <hi>To the Left,</hi> 4 times.</item>
                  <item>8. <hi>To the Left-about.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>9. <hi>As you were.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>10. <hi>Advance your Pike.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>In doing this, make your right Heel come up to your left Inſtep, having your Pike be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you, fall out with your right Foot, and bring your Pike to your right Thigh.</p>
               <p n="11">11. <hi>Shoulder.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Your fingers of your left hand being ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, lay that hand on your Pike even with your Shoulder, then make your right Heel come even with your left Inſtep, your Pike right before you, fall back with your right Leg, and put back your right Arm as far as may be, holding your Pike about half a foot from your ſide, keeping your Eye upon the Spear, and that directly to the Rear, your Pike ſlooped, when forſakeing it with your left hand, bring in your right Leg, laying your Pike on your right Shoulder, keeping your Elbow to your Body, the butt end a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout half a foot from the ground in the middle of the diſtance.</p>
               <p n="12">12. <hi>Charge to the Front.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Here you muſt fall back with your right Leg, putting back as much as may be your Arm, keeping the Spear exactly to the Rear,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:64196:13"/> ſetting the Pike aſlope at the ſame height as ſhouldering, then bring the butt end back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards with your left hand, turning the head with your right hand, then quit it with that hand, and take hold of the butt end, and Charge breaſt high, the palm of your hand againſt the butt end open, and your left El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bow under the Pike, the left Toe directly with the Spear, and when you Charge, let it be directly forward, your left Heel being juſt againſt the middle of your right Foot.</p>
               <p n="13">13. <hi>Shoulder as you were,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the firſt place, raiſe your Pike with both your hands, then quit it with the right, and with the left, turn the head backwards, the Spear directly with the Rear, then ſeize it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain with your right hand as high as you can reach without ſtraining, and ſtand with it from your Body aſlope, bring up your right Leg, and forſaking your Pike with your left hand, lay it on your Shoulder, always keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Spear in a direct point to the Rear, not any ways croſſing others.</p>
               <p n="14">14. <hi>Charge to the Right.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Here you muſt fall back with your right Arm and Leg, keep the Spear in the Rear, ſloped at the height of ſhouldering, turning your left Toe to the right, let the right fall behind the left, that the middle of your right Foot may be over againſt your left Heel, and in this Action bring your Pike up, and turn
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:64196:14"/> backwards the butt end by your right ſide, then preſſing it in the palm of your right hand, <hi>Charge.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="15">15. <hi>Shoulder, as you were.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Make your left Toe come to the left, and the middle of your right Foot againſt your left Heel, with your Pike up, then turn the head of it to the right, <hi>viz.</hi> directly to the Rear, doing it at one motion, then with your right hand take hold of your Pike, ſo with both hands keep it a little diſtance from your Body ſlop'd, as when you Shoulder, then bring your right Leg up, and lay your Pike on your Shoulder.</p>
               <p n="17">17. <hi>Charge to the Right-about.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Here you muſt with your Hand and Leg give back, and ſtand with your Pike a little diſtance from your ſide, turn your left Toe to the Right-about, bringing the butt end of your Pike to the right ſide, falling back with your right Leg, <hi>Chharge,</hi> keeping the Spear of your Pike all the while to the Rear a ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering height, being careful not to mount the Spear of your Pike higher or lower; and when you are to face to the Right-about level your Pike and <hi>Charge.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="17">17. <hi>As you were.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Upon this word of Command, turn your left Toe to the Left-about, cauſing your right Foot to advance a moderate ſtep, ſo that the middle of it be placed againſt your left
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:64196:14"/> Heel, bring the butt end with your left hand by your left ſide, obſerving the Spear to be exactly with the Rear, the ſame height as in ſhouldering, then as high as with eaſe you can reach, lay on your right hand, and ſtand with it in form, after which bring up your right Leg and Shoulder.</p>
               <p n="18">18. <hi>Charge to the Left.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In doing this poſture, fall back with your Leg and Arm, as has been ſhewed in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Chargings, turn to the left Toe, and turn the butt end of your Pike with your left hand to the Right, then bring up your right Leg and Charge.</p>
               <p n="19">19. <hi>As you were.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Here you muſt raiſe the Spear with both your hands, turning the left Toe to the Right, then fall back with your right Leg and Arm, holding your Pike from your ſide, the Spear directly to the Rear, then bring up your right Leg and Shoulder.</p>
               <p n="20">20. <hi>Charge to the Left-about.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In this caſe, fall back with your Leg and Arm, then bring the Pike over your head with both your hands, keeping the Spear di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly to the Rear at the height of ſhoulder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, turn your left Toe to the Left-about, then bring up your right Foot, ſo that the middle of it may come with your left Heel and <hi>Charge.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="21">
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:64196:15"/>21. <hi>Port.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Do this as charging the Front, but be cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, that you ſink not the Spear of your Pike ſo low, reſting it inſtead of the Elbow between the Thumb and Fore-finger, keeping the Elbow cloſe to your ſide.</p>
               <p n="22">22. <hi>Comport.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In this doing, you muſt bring your left hand backward as far as you may, ſtretching out the right, making thereupon a ſtep for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward with the right Foot, firmly graſping the Pike with the right hand as far as you can reach, not toſſing the Spear too high, this done, forſake it with your left hand, bringing back your right Leg even with your Left, then cloſe the Pike to your ſide, keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Spear about the height of your Head.</p>
               <p n="23">23. <hi>Charge to the Front.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In performing this, let your right Arm be extended at the ſame time, advancing your right Leg putting back your left hand as far as you can, bring your Pike forward, upon which give a ſtep back with your right Leg, take hold of the butt end with your right hand, then <hi>Charge,</hi> Charging ever breaſt high.</p>
               <p n="24">24. <hi>Fire.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Here you muſt face to the Right-about, ſuffering the Spear of your Pike to fall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind you, then let your right hand be quitted
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:64196:15"/> from the butt end, without moving the Left; take care likewiſe not to ſtrike up the Spear.</p>
               <p n="25">25. <hi>Charge as you were.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In this Exerciſe, turn your ſelf to the Left-about, take the butt end of the Pike on the palm of your right hand and Charge, keeping your Spear at an even height.</p>
               <p n="26">26. <hi>Advance your Pikes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Here you muſt obſerve to bring your right Heel to your left Inſtep, as likewiſe your Pike before you to the <hi>Recovery,</hi> then fall out with your right Foot, till it come even with your Left, and by this means bring your Pike to your right Thigh.</p>
               <p n="27">27. <hi>Order your Pikes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Raiſe your left hand even with the top of your ſhoulder, and lay it upon your Pike, your fingers ſtretched out, then ſink your left hand, and raiſe your right, and ſo raiſe the Pike, that when the butt end is on the ground, your right hand may be againſt your Eye, ſetting the butt end to the Latchet of your Shoe, and keeping the Pike near your Head: and in this Exerciſe ſuffer all the butt ends to fall to the ground together.</p>
               <p n="28">28. <hi>Pikes to your Inſide Order.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In this doing, you muſt fix the butt end of your Pike on the inſide of your right Foot to the middle, moving only your Pike, and not your Foot.</p>
               <p n="29">
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:64196:16"/>29. <hi>Lay down your Pikes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Here ſtep altogether with your right Legs, ſtoop all together with a quick motion, and lay them very ſtraight with your right hands.</p>
               <p n="30">30. <hi>Quit your Pikes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>With your left Leg fall back, bringing it even with your right, and ſtand up all to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether.</p>
               <p n="31">31. <hi>Handle your Pikes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In this doing, ſtep forward with your left Legs, in a quick motion, ſtoop all together, and extending your right hands as far as you can reach, graſp your Pike.</p>
               <p n="32">32. <hi>Order your Pikes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Raiſe the Pike with your right hand, ſtep back with your left Leg, clapping the butt end for the more eaſie raiſing about the middle of your right Foot on the inſide.</p>
               <p n="33">33. <hi>Pikes to your Out-ſide Order.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To do this place, the butt end of your Pike on the outſide your Foot, moving your Pike, and not your Foot.</p>
               <p n="34">34. <hi>Advance.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Do this as before: And thus have we given the Practitioner in Arms, The true Poſtures of the Musket and Pike diſtinctly, which with a little uſe, may perfect him in that which is ſo neceſſary to be underſtood by the Sons of <hi>Mars,</hi> from which we proceed to give further Inſtructions of this kind.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:64196:16"/>
               <head>Directions for the Exerciſe of the <hi>Pike</hi> and <hi>Musket</hi> together by a whole Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talion, or ſingle Company, ſuppoſing the <hi>Pikes</hi> Advanced, and <hi>Muskets</hi> Shouldered: The word of Command given is,</head>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Musketeers make Ready.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>IN this caſe, they muſt perform all the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtures and motions directly together, till ſuch time as they ſtand gaurded with their Muskets before them, and their Thumbs for the better ſecurity on the Cocks, whereupon the Pikes are to be recovered before the Pike<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, the butt ends in the palms of their hands, and the Spears upright, their left hands no more than the height of their Mouths.</p>
               <p>When the word <hi>Charge</hi> is given, then muſt they bring down the Muskets and Pikes at once, being ſure to turn the left Toes that way they Charge, and the heel of the fame Foot directly againſt the middle of the right Foot in every Charge, charging directly for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, not at firſt charging, the Pikes cloſe to one anothers Breaſts, but charge a little way diſtant in bringing down the Pikes, and
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:64196:17"/> when they are charged, then is the time to cloſe them.</p>
               <p>The Charge is, <hi>To the Right</hi> four times, Then <hi>to the Right-about,</hi> after that, <hi>As you were,</hi> Then <hi>to the Left Charge</hi> four times, Then <hi>to the Left-about Charge,</hi> Then <hi>as you were,</hi> which you may plainly obſerve in what has been laid down in the former Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe.</p>
               <p>Here the Pike-men muſt turn as the Mus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keteers, bringing up their right Heels to their left Inſteps, extending their Arms as they turn, bringing their Muskets ſtraight be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them, their left hand as high as their Mouths, pulling back their Arms, and when they are faced, fall back with their right Legs, nor muſt the Souldiers bring down their Arms till the word <hi>Charge</hi> is given, doing it with a quick motion, and not ſuffering the Pikes to clatter.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Then the word of Command is,</hi> viz.
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Recover your Arms.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Half bend your Muskets.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Poiſe your Muskets.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Shoulder your Musket.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>As before is noted.</p>
               <p>Hereupon, the Muskets being Shouldered, the Pikes that ſtood Recovered falling out with their right Legs, the Pikes are brought to their Thighs to their Advance.</p>
               <list>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:64196:17"/>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Poiſe your Muskets.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>This Command given, the Pike-men muſt fix their left hands to their Pikes about the height of their Shoulders. Then</p>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Order your Arms.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Pikes to your Inſide Order.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Lay down your Arms.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Quit your Arms.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>To the Right-about.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>March.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>Theſe muſt be obſerved, as is before di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected in the Exerciſe, which to repeat again would be Tautology, only thus much when you are clear of your Arms, you muſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſe, and upon the beat of Drum run thither again with a Huzza, your Swords drawn, and their points upwards: Then theſe words of Command are given, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Return your Swords.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Handle your Arms.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Order your Arms.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Pikes to your Out-ſide Order.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Advance.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>Theſe things ought to be duly conſidered, and in this firſt place, in ordering your Arms, obſerve to make a little ſtop before the butt ends come to the ground, that they may fall to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether at once; after the Arms are laid down and quitted, you muſt all ſtand up together, as if it were but one motion.</p>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:64196:18"/>
               <p>Upon marching from your Arms, ſtep Front and Rear together with the left Feet, and march but a little diſtance.</p>
               <p>Your right hands being laid on your Swords, you muſt take hold of your Scabbards with your left hands, and your Swords being drawn, you muſt hold them upright before you, bringing them down at one motion, and when by Command you have returned your Swords, you muſt ſtand upright to your Arms, looking to your proper Front. As for the reſt, we refer you to the Exerciſe of the Pike and Musket diſtinctly.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Several things to be obſerved in Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand and Exerciſe relating to the <hi>Match-Lock, Musket,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
               <p>THE Match-Lock Musket in all the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terial parts of Exerciſe is the ſame with the Fire-Lock; but ſome other things being to be obſerved, we ſhall lay them down for the eaſe of the Reader, and this chiefly conſiſts in keeping your Match well with a good Coal, faſtning it upon Command, advantagiouſly in your Screw, blowing the Coal, and trying your Pan by falſe flaſhes, laying it down at Command, taking it up again, ſhortening it
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:64196:18"/> to the Pan, that it may give true Fire: But more to the particulars.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Lay down your Matches.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Do this at four Motions, firſt by a little turning the butt end of your Musket eaſily, ſlipping on your Shoulder, lay then your right hand on your Match: In the next place, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend your right hand and foot before you, and recover your Musket in its place. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſtoop and bring your Match near the right Foot, within-ſide, ſuffering your Ham to bend a little. Laſtly, quit it, and bring your Body upright, and your right Foot even with your left.</p>
               <p n="2">2. When the Command is given, <hi>viz. <hi>Handle your Match,</hi>
                  </hi> then having recovered it, bring it between your third and fourth Finger by the help of your Thumb and firſt Finger, always uſing your right Hand then the Palm being turned from you, you ſtretch your Arm towards your right hand Man.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Blow your Match.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Hereupon bring your Match to your Mouth, not ſtooping, but turning your Head a little to the right, when having given a ſtrong Blaſt to carry off the Aſhes, caſt off your Arm to the right.</p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>Cock and try your Match.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In this caſe, fetching a compaſs with your Arm, bring your Match to the Cock, and ſupporting it with your two near Fingers,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:64196:19"/> preſs it down with your Thumb, guiding i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> with your middle Finger, when keeping you<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> middle finger, between it and the Pan, pul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> your Cock down as low as the Pan, and ſink or raiſe your Match, that it may hit the middle of the Pan, and having fired when you hear the word.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Return your Match.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Hold your Musket in your left hand, the Barrel towards you, ſuffering your left Elbow to reſt on your Body, then take your Match between your Thumb and Finger in the right hand, placing your Thumb on the top of it, the palm being turned from you, placing one end of your Match between the third and fourth finger of your left hand, and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther end preſs with the firſt and ſecond fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, then with extended fingers place your right hand under the Pan.</p>
               <p>This is all that is material as to the Match, the other poſtures of the Musket being the ſame with the Fire-Lock already mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:64196:19"/>
               <head>Directions for the Exerciſe of Foot Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nadiers.</head>
               <p>THough the Granadiers in many things differ from the Musketiers in Exerciſe, yet for the better part they do the ſame, draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up in the ſame Order, Rank and File, only they ſeldom draw up above three deep, and ſuppoſing then to be ſhouldered. The words of Command are,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lay your right Hands on your Fire-Locks.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Poiſe your Fire-Locks.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Reſt your Fire-Locks.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Cock your Fire-Locks.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>Gaurd your Fire-Locks.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>Preſent.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6. <hi>Fire.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7. <hi>Recover your Arms.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>All theſe are to be done in the ſame man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner as the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of the Fire-Lock, Musket.</p>
               <p n="8">8. <hi>Caſt over to the Left.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In doing this, they are to lay their right hands on their Daggers.</p>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:64196:20"/>
               <p n="9">9. <hi>Draw your Daggers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Here they muſt draw their Dag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers and hold them upright in their hands be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them.</p>
               <p n="10">10. <hi>Screw it into the Muzle of your Fire-Lock.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Do this ſo, that the flat ſide may be to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards you when you have recovered.</p>
               <p n="11">11. <hi>Return your Arms.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="12">12. <hi>Charge to the Right</hi> (four times.)</p>
               <p n="13">13. <hi>To the Right-about, Charge.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="14">14. <hi>As you were.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="15">15. <hi>To the left Charge</hi> (four times.)</p>
               <p n="16">16. <hi>To the Left-about Charge.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="17">17. <hi>As you were.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="18">18. <hi>Recover your Arms.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe are to be done with a quick Motion after the manner of the Fire-Lock, Musket.</p>
               <p n="19">19. <hi>Caſt to your Left.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Upon this, they are to ſeize their Daggers with their right hands.</p>
               <p n="20">20. <hi>Withdraw your Daggers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Hereupon hold them directly before you, the flat ſide to your Body.</p>
               <p n="21">21. <hi>Return your Daggers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Upon this, put them up into the Scab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bard.</p>
               <p n="22">
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:64196:20"/>22. <hi>Poiſe your Fire-Lock.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="23">23. <hi>Half bend your Fire-Lock.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Do theſe as the Musketiers do the Fire-Lock.</p>
               <p n="24">24, <hi>Open your Cartridge-Box, and handle your Primer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe are eaſily underſtood, and need no direction.</p>
               <p n="25">25. <hi>Prime.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="26">26. <hi>Return your Primer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="27">27. <hi>Shut your Pan.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="28">28. <hi>Blow off your looſe Corns.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="30">30. <hi>Caſt about to Charge.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Do all theſe as the Musketiers.</p>
               <p n="31">31. <hi>Handle your Cartridge.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="32">32. <hi>Open it with your Teeth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="33">33. <hi>Charge with Powder and Ball.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="34">34. <hi>Draw forth your Scowerer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="35">35. <hi>Shorten it to an Inch.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Here, by the Cartridge is meant, the Charge of Powder made up in a paper fit for the Peice, ſo that the Bullet being placed on the top of it, they may be put in together.</p>
               <p n="36">36. <hi>Ram down Powder and Ball.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="37">37. <hi>Withdraw your Scowerer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="38">38. <hi>Shorten it to a handful.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="39">39. <hi>Return your Scowerer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="40">40. <hi>Poiſe your Fire-Lock.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Do theſe as the Musketiers do, according to the Inſtructions laid down, in their Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe.</p>
               <p n="41">
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:64196:21"/>41. <hi>Shoulder your Fire-Locks.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Upon this Command, the Ranks are to cloſe forward at ſix foot, it being the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeants care to place their Halberts at a due diſtance.</p>
               <p n="42">42. <hi>Poiſe your Fire-Locks.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Upon this, over and above what the Mus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket requires, ſeize the ſling with your left hand.</p>
               <p n="43">43. <hi>Sling your Fire-Locks.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="44">44. <hi>Handle your Pouches.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In handling your Pouches, let your left hands be on the bottom, all of a height, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancing the right Legs, and the right hands being of an equal height.</p>
               <p n="45">45. <hi>Open your Pouches.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Do this altogether.</p>
               <p n="46">46. <hi>Take forth your Granadoes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Do this with the right hand extended be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you.</p>
               <p n="47">47. <hi>Shut your Pouches.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Do this all at once.</p>
               <p n="48">48. <hi>Vncaſe your Fuzee.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Doing this, ſtep back with the right foot to the left facing.</p>
               <p n="49">49. <hi>Handle your Match.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Do this with the left hand to the left ſide, extending your Arms, doing it nimbly alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether.</p>
               <p n="50">
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:64196:21"/>50. <hi>Blow your Match.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In this doing, the firſt Rank muſt fall back with their right Legs altogether, giving a ſtrong Blaſt.</p>
               <p n="51">51. <hi>Fire your Fuzee.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="52">52. <hi>Deliver your Granado.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>At this laſt word of Command, the ſecond Rank muſt advance ſix foot before the firſt with their Match ready to blow; and when they have obſerved the words of Command, the third muſt advance before them, when upon the word, <hi>Blow your March,</hi> the firſt and ſecond Ranks are to lay their hands upon their Hatchets; and uppn the word, <hi>Fire your Fuzees,</hi> they are to raiſe their Hatchets; and upon that of <hi>Deliver your Granado,</hi> the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeants muſt be careful that the firſt Rank ſtands, the ſecond Marches ſix Foot before the firſt, and the third ſix foot before the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, expecting the word of Command with their Hatchets raiſed, at what time the firſt Rank muſt raiſe theirs likewiſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fall on.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In this caſe they muſt handle them faſt, bringing them down.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Return your Hatchets.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Upon this you muſt put them into the frog of your Belt by your ſide.</p>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:64196:22"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Poiſe your Fire-Locks.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Shoulder your Fire-Locks.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Do theſe as in caſe of the Fire-Lock, Musket.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Granadiers make Ready.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In this caſe the firſt Rank muſt make ready their Fire-Locks, and the ſecond Rank handle their Pouches, and the third their Hatchets</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The firſt Rank preſent.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>At this word of Command, the ſecond Rank muſt open their Pouches, take thence their Granadoes, whilſt the third raiſe their Hatchets.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fire.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Upon this, word of Command, the ſecond Rank muſt ſhut their Pouches, uncaſe their Fuzes, and handle their Match.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Recover your Arms.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Here without any further Command, the Granadiers of the firſt Rank muſt caſt over to the Left, draw and ſcrew their Daggers into the Muzles of their Peices, Recover their Arms and Charge; the ſecond Rank to advance ſix foot before them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Blow your Match.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fire your Fuzee.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Deliver your Granadoe.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:64196:22"/>
               <p>Upon this laſt Command, they are to Poiſe their Fire-Locks, and make ready, whilſt the third March as the ſecond with their Hat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fall on.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Recover your Arms.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>At this laſt, the third Rank muſt march twelve foot before the firſt Charging, the ſecond at ſix, the firſt returning their Hat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chets, and making ready their Fire-Locks.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Recover your Arms.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Upon this they are to half bend their Fire-Locks.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Caſt over to the Left.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Withdraw your Daggers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Return your Daggers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Poiſe your Fire-Lock.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Shoulder your Fire: Lock.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Face to the Right-about.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>March.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Upon this laſt 'tis the Serjeants duty to be careful, that forward the Ranks open to twelve foot, and that they ſo continue march<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing till they come to their Ground, where they muſt halt without any word or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand.</p>
               <list>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:64196:23"/>
                  <head>In theſe ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture of the Musket.</head>
                  <item>
                     <hi>As you were.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Poiſe your Fire-Locks.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Order your Arms.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Lay down your Arms.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Quit your Arms.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Face to the Right about.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>March.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>Here obſerve, that when you are clear of your Arms, you are to diſperſe, and upon the Drum beating, you muſt haſt to your Arms with a chearful Huzza, your Daggers drawn, lifted with their Points upwards.</p>
               <list>
                  <head>Obſerve theſe as the Exerciſe of the Musket, Fire-Lock, and the reſt as they have been laid down, and you may grow ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pert.</head>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Return your Dagger.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Handle your Arms.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Order your Arms.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Poiſe your Fire-Locks.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Shoulder your Fire-Locks.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:64196:23"/>
               <head>Conſiderations of the Drum ſo neceſſary in the Exerciſe of the Foot, what re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates thereto.</head>
               <p>THE Drum has been very anciently uſed in War, and always approved by the greateſt Captains; the Souldiers underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thereby, what they are to do in many points, as well as by the voice of their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander, and therefore it is called ſeme-vocal, and gives directions of ſundry kinds in theſe ſix points of War more peculiarly diſtinguiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. The <hi>Call.</hi> 2. The <hi>Troop.</hi> 3. The <hi>March.</hi> 4. The <hi>Preparative.</hi> 5. The <hi>Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taile.</hi> 6. The <hi>Retreat.</hi> And of theſe in their Order.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The <hi>Call</hi> is to bring the Souldiers toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to their Arms upon deliberate or urgent occaſions, or to hear any Proclamation or Orders that are to be given by the Officers; ſo the Souldiers ought not, eſpecially in time of War, on great Penalties, to ramble be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the hearing of it, unleſs they be ſent upon Parties, or by ſome Expreſs, with the Knowledge and Approbation of the General or Officer in Chief.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The <hi>Troop</hi> being beat, the Souldiers muſt incontinently ſhoulder their Muskets,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:64196:24"/> and Advance their Pikes, cloſing their Ranks and Files to Order, following their Officers to the place of Randesvoze, or elſe where.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The <hi>March</hi> beaten, you muſt obſerve to take your open Order in Rank, ſhoulder both Musket and Pike, and march quicker, or ſlower, as the Drum beats.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The <hi>Preparative</hi> is to warn you, that you cloſe your due diſtance in preparing for Battle, or Skirmiſh, and ſee that nothing be out of Order that may turn to your Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage or Hindrance, for a Battle ſeldom ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds well where the Order is not obſerved with the greateſt Exactneſs.</p>
               <p n="5">5. The <hi>Battle</hi> is that which is uſually called the Charge or Signal, to Charge the Enemy; ſo that upon this the Souldier muſt raiſe his Spirit to the higheſt pitch of Fury, though with caution, for Valour and Prudence ought to go hand in hand, if you would attain to things noble and great.</p>
               <p n="6">6. The <hi>Retreat.</hi> This is beat when at any time the Enemy is too ſtrong, or by drawing off to better your ground, you may gain a better Advantage, or expect greater Succour, as when an Out-guard or Party finds it ſelf over-charged, it Retreats to the main Body, or when on a ſudden, an advanced Party eſpies an Ambuſhment.</p>
               <p>Beſides theſe, there are two others uſed, but they are not properly called Points of War, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:64196:24"/>
               <head>The Tatto, or Tapto, and the Revalley.</head>
               <p>The firſt of theſe is uſed in a Garriſon, or upon the Rounds, both to warn the Souldiers and Inhabitants, when they ought to repair to their Quarters, or Guard, and when to ſhut the Doors, that ſo if any Spies be abroad, they may be the better diſtinguiſhed; for when the Tapto is returned to the Body of Gaurds, a warning Peice ought to be ſhot off, after which no perſon ought to be out of his Quarters, or from his Poſt, unleſs the Watch-word be given him.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Revalley</hi> takes, as is moſt likely, its Denomination from the <hi>French</hi> word <hi>Reveiller,</hi> which ſignifies as much, as to ariſe up, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wake from ſleep, for this is beaten in the Morning, to give notice to the People, that they may be ſafely abroad, at which time the Out-Centinels are taken off.</p>
               <p>There are of late other things ſignified by the Drum, as the manner of Exerciſe, but it being moſtly according to Humour, the Drum-Majors ought to give it to every File-leader in writing, that ſo he may be able to direct his File by his Example, what they are to do till the Souldiers are perfect in it, and the reaſon why we ſo direct is, becauſe it is variable, and not ſo ſubſtantial as the word of Command.</p>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:64196:25"/>
               <p>There are at this day in many Regiments <hi>Hoitheys</hi> uſed inſtead of the ancient <hi>Flutes,</hi> but they have no ſignificant Sign, being only to chear and raiſe the Spirits of the Souldiers, that their labour may ſeem the leſs.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The Exerciſe of Dragoons or Musketiers on Horſe-back.</head>
               <p>IN this, to ſhorten any tedious Prologue or Intricacy, we will ſuppoſe the Dragoons to be ready in the Field, drawn up in three Ranks, having advanced their Muskets, the Officers taken their Stations, and all things in a readineſs for the word of Command.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Dragoons have a care.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Sling your Muskets.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Make ready your Links.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>Clear your right Foot of your Stir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rop.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>Diſmount.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Here they muſt ſtand ready at their Horſes heads, and the ſix out-ſide men continue mounted, that ſo they may hold and guard the Horſes.</p>
               <p n="6">6. <hi>Link your Horſes to the Left.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7. <hi>March clear off your Horſes, and Shoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der as you March.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="8">8. <hi>Halt.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:64196:25"/>
               <p>Upon theſe words of Command, the Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talion by the care of the Officers, is to be formed as the Foot, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Have a care of the Exerciſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Officers to the Right-about.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Take your Poſts in the Rear of the Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>March.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In this Ordering, the Serjeants and Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porals muſt fall into the Flank, and Rear of the Battalion, and the Commiſſion Officers form a Rank in the Rear.</p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>Dragoons have a care.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Upon this they muſt pull off their Gloves of the right hand, and ſtick them in their Girdles.</p>
               <p n="6">6. <hi>Lay your right hand to your Muskets.</hi> 7. <hi>Poiſe your Muskets.</hi> 8. <hi>Reſt your Mus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kets.</hi> 9. <hi>Cock and Guard.</hi> 10. <hi>Preſent.</hi> 11. <hi>Fire.</hi> 12. <hi>Recover your Arms with the Cock half Bent.</hi> 13. <hi>Reſt upon your Muskets.</hi> 14. <hi>Handle your Daggers.</hi> 15. <hi>Draw forth your Daggers.</hi> 16. <hi>Fix them in the Muzle of your Muskets.</hi> 17. <hi>Poiſe your Muskets.</hi> 18. <hi>Charge to the Front,</hi> 19. <hi>To the Right, Charge,</hi> (four times.) 20. <hi>To the Right-about, Charge.</hi> 21. <hi>To the Left-about Charge.</hi> 22. <hi>To the Left Charge</hi> (four times) 23. <hi>To the Left-about Charge.</hi> 24. <hi>To the Right-about, Charge.</hi> 25. <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover your Arms.</hi> 26. <hi>Reſt upon your Muskets.</hi>
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:64196:26"/> 27. <hi>Handle your Daggers.</hi> 28. <hi>Withdraw your Daggers.</hi> 29. <hi>Place your Daggers.</hi> 30. <hi>Poiſe your Muskets.</hi> 31. <hi>Reſt your Muskets.</hi> 32. <hi>Clean your Pans.</hi> 33. <hi>Open your Cartridge Box.</hi> 34. <hi>Handle your Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer.</hi> 35. <hi>Sink and Prime.</hi> 36. <hi>Return your Primer.</hi> 37. <hi>Shut your Pan with your Fore-fingers.</hi> 38. <hi>Blow off your looſe Corns;</hi> At which time you muſt Recover your Arms. 39. <hi>Caſt about to Charge.</hi> 40. <hi>Handle your Cartridge.</hi> 41. <hi>Take out your Cartridges;</hi> which done, you muſt preſently ſhut the Box. 42. <hi>Open them with your Teeth.</hi> 43. <hi>Charge with Powder and Ball.</hi> 44. <hi>Draw forth your Scowerers.</hi> 45. <hi>Shorten them to an Inch.</hi> This muſt be done againſt your Breath. 46. <hi>Put it into the Muzle of your Musket.</hi> 47. <hi>Ram down Powder and Ball.</hi> 48. <hi>Withdraw your Scowerer.</hi> 49. <hi>Shor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten it to an Inch,</hi> as before. 50. <hi>Place your Scowerer.</hi> 51. <hi>Moiſe your Muskets.</hi> 52. <hi>Shoulder your Muskets.</hi> 53. <hi>Poiſe your Musket.</hi> 54. <hi>Reſt your Musket.</hi> 55. <hi>Lay down your Arms.</hi> 56. <hi>Quit your Arms.</hi> 57. <hi>To the Right-about.</hi> 58. <hi>March clear off your Arms and break:</hi> Being marched clear off the Arms, they muſt offer, as if they diſperſed; but upon the firſt beat of Drum they muſt ſwiftly return with a Huzza, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one drawing (in that motion) his Sword, then each muſt ſtand over his own Arms, to
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:64196:26"/> expect further Command, <hi>viz.</hi> 59. <hi>Return your Swords.</hi> 60. <hi>Handle your Arms.</hi> 61. <hi>Reſt upon your Arms.</hi> 62. <hi>Poiſe your Mus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kets.</hi> 63. <hi>Sling your Muskets.</hi> 64. <hi>To the Right-about.</hi> 65. <hi>March to your Horſes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> 66. <hi>Vnlink your Horſes.</hi> 67. <hi>Shorten your Bridles.</hi> 68. <hi>Put your left Foot in your Stirrup.</hi> 69. <hi>Mount.</hi> 70. <hi>Faſten your Links.</hi> 71. <hi>Vnſling, and Advance your Muskets.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Though this Exerciſe is for the moſt part like the Exerciſe of the Fire-Lock, Musket, on Foot, whether to know any thing difficult; we refer you, yet theſe are many times obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to fight on Horſe-back, as being appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and neceſſary for the ſuccour, either of Horſe or Foot, as occaſion or advantage of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers; therefore it will be requiſit to ſpeak ſomething of their fireing on Horſe-back.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The Exerciſe of Dragoons on Horſe-back, as to their Fireing, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THE Dragoons having advanced their Muskets on their right Thigh, muſt expect the words of Command, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Ioyn your left hand to your Musket,</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Cock and Guard.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:64196:27"/>3. <hi>Reſt your Muskets on your Bridle hand.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>Preſent.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>Fire.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6. <hi>Recover your Arms with the Cock halt bent.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This being obſerved, they are in a poſture to March, Wheel, or Face, as ſhall be Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, or ſeen moſt Expedient.</p>
               <p>Theſe Dragoons were at firſt entertained for ſwift Marches, paſſing deep Ways or Waters, to keep equal pace with the Horſe, till the Foot at more leaſure could come up; but being ſince found very neceſſary to defend againſt the ſhot of the Musketiers, they have been continued, and are no more than a kind of Musketiers on Horſe-back.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Granadiers on Horſe-back, what their Exerciſe is, and how to perform it with Dexterity. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THeſe, as the Dragoons often fight on Foot, and therefore, though, when they are on Horſe-back, they may be Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed as the Horſe; yet it is moſt convenient whenever they March, Wheel, Face, or Halt, that they do not bear up too cloſe, nor do it in thick Files, but between every File
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:64196:27"/> leave three foot diſtance at leaſt, the eaſier to diſmount, and March clear off their Hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, or Face about as occaſion ſhall require, when in this manner being marched into the Field with their Arms loaden, Hats on, and the the word to <hi>Halt</hi> given, the Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Officer having bid Silence, muſt thus pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Granadiers have a care.</hi> 2. <hi>Sling your Muskets.</hi> In this doing, have your left hand upon your Sling. 3. <hi>Put on your Caps.</hi> 4. <hi>Right and Left-hand Men of each Rank, keep Mounted.</hi> 5. <hi>Clear your right Foot off the Stirrup.</hi> In this caſe they muſt handle their Muskets, caſting them backwards. 6. <hi>Diſmount.</hi> This muſt be done altogether with a quick motion. 7. <hi>Make ready your Links.</hi> 8. <hi>Link your Horſes to the Left.</hi> 9. <hi>March clear off your Horſes.</hi> This may be done by a third or ſecond Rank, marching through as ſoon as clear, handling at the ſame time their Muskets. 10. <hi>Halt.</hi> 11. <hi>Lay your right hands on your Muskets.</hi> 12. <hi>Poiſe your Muskets, facing to the Right.</hi> 13. <hi>Reſt your Muskets.</hi> 14. <hi>Cock and Guard.</hi> 15. <hi>Preſent.</hi> 16. <hi>Fire.</hi> 17. <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover your Arms.</hi> Here you muſt have your Muskets half bent. 18. <hi>Caſt about to the Left.</hi> 19. <hi>Draw your Dagger.</hi> 20. <hi>Fix them in your Muskets.</hi> 21. <hi>Recover your Arms.</hi> 22. <hi>Charge to the Front.</hi> 23. <hi>To
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:64196:28"/> the Right, Charge</hi> (four times) 24. <hi>To the Right-about, Charge.</hi> 25. <hi>As you were.</hi> 26. <hi>To the Left, Charge</hi> (four times.) 27. <hi>To the Left-about.</hi> 28. <hi>As you were.</hi> 29. <hi>Recover your Arms.</hi> 30. <hi>Caſt about to the Left:</hi> Hold, on this word of Command, your right hands on your Daggers. 31. <hi>With<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw your Daggers.</hi> 32. <hi>Return your Dag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers.</hi> 33. <hi>Poiſe your Muskets.</hi> 34. <hi>Clean your Pan.</hi> 35. <hi>Open your Cartridge Box.</hi> 36. <hi>Take out your Primer.</hi> 37. <hi>Prime.</hi> 38. <hi>Return your Primer.</hi> 39. <hi>Shut your Pan.</hi> In doing this, bring your Piece up quick be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you. 40. <hi>Blow off your looſe Corns.</hi> 41. <hi>Caſt about to Charge.</hi> 42. <hi>Take out your Cartridges,</hi> immediately ſhutting the Boxes. 43. <hi>Vncap your Cartridge with your Teeth.</hi> 44. <hi>Load with Powder and Ball.</hi> 45. <hi>Draw forth your Scowerer.</hi> 46. <hi>Shor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten it to an Inch.</hi> 47. <hi>Place it in the Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel.</hi> 48. <hi>Ram home Powder and Ball.</hi> 49. <hi>Withdraw your Scowerer.</hi> 50. <hi>Shorten it to a handful.</hi> 51. <hi>Return your Scowerer.</hi> 52. <hi>Poiſe your Musket,</hi> (Do this before you.) 53. <hi>Shoulder your Musket.</hi> Upon this word, ſeize the Slings with your left hands. 54. <hi>Sling your Muskets.</hi> 55. <hi>Handle your Pouches;</hi> the ſame with the Foot Granadiers. 56. <hi>Open your Pouches.</hi> 57. <hi>Take forth your Granadoe.</hi> In doing this, extend your right hand before you. 58. <hi>Shut your
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:64196:28"/> Pouches.</hi> Do this, that it may appear but one Motion, the left hands being held-up all at a height. 59. <hi>Wncaſe your Fuzee.</hi> In do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this, you muſt face to the Front, having fallen back with your right Leg, bringing it even with the Left. 60. <hi>Handle your Match.</hi> 61. <hi>Blow your Match.</hi> 62. <hi>The firſt Rank, Fire your Fuzee.</hi> 63. <hi>Deliver your Granadoe.</hi> Upon this Delivery, you muſt unſling your Muskets.</p>
               <p>At this Command, the ſecond Rank muſt advance through the Right, having their Match in Order, ready to blow and place themſelves ſix Foot before the Rank.</p>
               <p n="64">64. <hi>Blow your Match.</hi> 65. <hi>Fire your Fuzee.</hi> 66. <hi>Deliver your Granadoe.</hi> Upon this your Musket being unſlung, you muſt ſtand ready Cockt and Guarded; then the third Rank is to march on the Right ſix foot frontward of the ſecond. 67. <hi>Blow your Match.</hi> 68. <hi>Fire your Fuzee.</hi> 69. <hi>Deliver your Granadoe.</hi> This done, unſling, and ſtand Cockt and Guarded; and upon this Command, the firſt or proper Front muſt ſpeedily March through at ſix foot diſtance. 71. <hi>Firſt Rank Fire.</hi> After this word, the firſt Rank muſt fix their Daggers in the Muzles of their Muskets, and the ſecond and third muſt imitate the firſt ſucceſſively, as the ſame words of Command come to their turn. 72. <hi>Recover your Arms.</hi> 73. <hi>Caſt about to the
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:64196:29"/> Left.</hi> 74. <hi>Withdraw your Daggers.</hi> 75. <hi>Poiſe your Muskets;</hi> doing it to the proper Front. 76. <hi>Shoulder your Muskets.</hi> 77. <hi>To the Right-about.</hi> In this doing, take up your firſt ground in your March, opening your Ranks. 79. <hi>To your Leader.</hi> 80. <hi>Poiſe your Muskets.</hi> 81. <hi>Reſt upon your Arms.</hi> 82. <hi>Lay down your Arms.</hi> 83. <hi>To the Right-about.</hi> 84. <hi>March.</hi> In marching, the Ranks muſt be broken in manner of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſing, then upon beat of Drum, you muſt draw your Swords, face about, recover your Order, and return to your Arms with a Huz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>za. 85. <hi>Return your Swords.</hi> 86. <hi>Handle your Arms.</hi> 87. <hi>Recover and Poiſe.</hi> 88. <hi>Shoulder your Muskets.</hi> 89. <hi>Poiſe your Muskets.</hi> 90. <hi>Face to the Right-about.</hi> 91. <hi>Sling your Muskets.</hi> 92. <hi>March your Horſes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In this laſt performance, the ſecond and third Ranks muſt March, and ſtanding at their Horſes heads, face to the Front.</p>
               <p n="93">93. <hi>Vnlink your your Horſes.</hi> 94. <hi>Faſten your Links.</hi> When this is done, you muſt ſhorten your Bridles. 95. <hi>Put your Feet in the Stirrups.</hi> Here you muſt lay your Mus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kets over your Sadles. 96. <hi>Mount your Hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes.</hi> This muſt be done altogether, as if it were but one Motion, and the Officers whoſe buſineſs it is, are to ſee the Ranks compleated in good Order. 97. <hi>Handle
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:64196:29"/> your Swords.</hi> 98. <hi>Draw your Swords.</hi> 99. <hi>Place your Swords.</hi> Here you muſt put your Sword into your Bridle hand. 100. <hi>Handle your Piſtol,</hi> which muſt be ever the Left. 101. <hi>Draw your Piſtol.</hi> 102. <hi>Cock your Piſtol.</hi> Here you muſt keep the Cock gaurded with your Thumb. 103. <hi>Preſent.</hi> In this doing, bear up your hand. even with the Cock. 104. <hi>Fire.</hi> Here you muſt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve not to take down your Piſtol, till the next word of Command, which is, 105. <hi>Return your Piſtol,</hi> and the ſame Order muſt be obſerved upon drawing the right Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtol, till you return it, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 106. <hi>Handle your Muskets.</hi> 107. <hi>Vnſling your Mus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kets.</hi> 108. <hi>Mount your Muskets.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If you are to Charge on Horſe-back with the Musket, which is not done but upon great oceaſion, the Peice being Charged, the words of Command are, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Cock your Muskets.</hi> 2. <hi>Preſent your Muskets.</hi> 3. <hi>Give Fire.</hi> In this doing, you muſt keep your Musket in its poſture, till the next word of Command, <hi>viz.</hi> 4. <hi>Sling your Muskets.</hi> 5. <hi>Handle your Swords.</hi> Do it by taking your Swords in your right hands. 6. <hi>March.</hi> In Marching, the Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers commanding, may bring them to any moving poſture, as Wheeling, Facing, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> by giving his words of Command with ſuch de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liberation, that thoſe who are more peculiar
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:64196:30"/> to take notice, may ſee each Individual Part, perform his Exerciſe, and that they mannag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> their Horſes as they ought.</p>
               <p>Theſe Inſtructions put in practice, ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> greatly forward the young Souldier, thoug<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> indeed, a heedful practice is the Life of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The Exerciſe of Horſe ſo properly called</head>
               <p>THough as to the words of Command i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Exerciſe, they are not many, yet vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous are the Actions to be performed by them, as after we have given an account of the known words of Command ſhall be ſhew'd at large, and in this caſe, when a Squadron or Troop is appointed to Exerciſe, having their Carbines and Piſtols Loaden, the Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porals muſt paſs through the Ranks, and ſee that they are all ready, which done, the Chief Officer commands Silence, and gives the words, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lay your right hands on your Sword.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Draw your Swords.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Put your Swords in your Bridle-hands.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lay your hands on your Piſtels.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cock your Piſtols.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hold up your Hands.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:64196:30"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Give Fire.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When you have given Fire, you muſt not let your Piſtol hand fall till the next word of Command be given, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Return your Piſtols.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And this you muſt obſeve in Fireing the right and Left again.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lay your hands on your Carbines.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Advance your Carbines.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cock your Carbines.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fire.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Let fall your Carbines.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Take your Swords from your Bridle-hands.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Return your Swords.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe motions muſt be exactly obſerved, every man doing each particular motion at one and the ſame time; the word of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand for that purpoſe, being given delibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately, that there may be no miſtake.</p>
               <p>In drawing up a Body of Horſe, that is, when the Body is drawn up, the Officers that command not in Chief ought to keep cloſe to their Men, but the Chief Commandant muſt be about a Horſes length before them, to ſee more exactly what is done; and ſo it muſt be obſerved in Marching: It is further to be noted at this day, that when a Squa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dron of Horſe is to Wheel; if to the Right, the right hand men muſt not cloſe to the Left as formerly, for that puts the Rank many
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:64196:31"/> times out of Order, but they muſt keep thei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Ground, ſuffering the left to come about whilſt they only turn their Horſes heads, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving their left hand Men.</p>
               <p>This may ſerve for the Motions, which the Officers are to take care of, yet there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains many other curious Matters, to which we proceed.</p>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>To Cloſe the Files.</head>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>1. If you would be at cloſe Files. To cloſe your Files,</hi> The righr Wing File ſtand Cloſe your Files. To the Right. To the Left. As you were. To the left Wing an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſtand. To the Left by Files cloſe the Squa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dron. To the Right. As you were. The righ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> and left Wing Files ſtand. By half Ranks cloſe Files to the right and left; <hi>or by cloſing Files, you may cleave the Squadron.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>The manner of Cloſing the Ranks.</head>
                  <p>File-Leaders ſtand. By Ranks cloſe the Squadron to the Front. On the Front as you were, or open to the Ranks on the Front to the firſt diſtances.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>The manner of doubling Ranks.</head>
                  <p>By half Files to the Right, Double your Ranks to the Front.</p>
                  <pb n="57" facs="tcp:64196:31"/>
                  <p>File Leaders Advance your Rank. Half Files take your Ground. <hi>In this manner you may Command to the Left.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The firſt half Files ſtand. By half File, Leaders on the left Wing double your Ranks to the Front.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Now if you would reduce this again, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the following Command, <hi>viz.</hi>
                     </hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Right Wing half Rank Advance your Ranks. Half File-Leader take your Ground. The firſt half File ſtand. By half File-Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders on the right and left Wings, then double your Ranks to the Front, <hi>Carocolling</hi> to the right and left, then the laſt half File ſtand, and the firſt half Files by <hi>Carocol</hi> to the right and left on the Wings, after this double your Ranks to the Rear.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Here the firſt half File muſt obſerve to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen the half Rank to the Right and Left. The firſt half File by</hi> Carocol, To the Right and Left double your Ranks to the Rear.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>In this caſe, let the laſt half File open the half Rank to the Right and Left; and ſince theſe words</hi> Carocol <hi>and</hi> Converſion <hi>may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear difficult to underſtand, it will be conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient to explain the Motion.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>When you are to Wheel by</hi> Carocol, <hi>ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve that it is made by the depth or flank of of the Squadron, by which means the Rank, and not the File makes the Motion.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="58" facs="tcp:64196:32"/>
                  <p>Converſion <hi>in Wheeling is performed by the Front of the Squadron, by which means the File remains whilſt the Rank makes the Motion.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Directions for Wheeling by <hi>Converſion</hi> with the Word of Command.</head>
               <p>WHen we ſay to the Right by <hi>Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,</hi> it is to be underſtood, That you ought to cloſe your Right Leg to the Horſe, your Knee touching that of the right hand man's, and ſo you muſt do in the word of Command to the Left, as when we ſay, <hi>Cloſe the Left Wing;</hi> then muſt the left Leg cloſed.</p>
               <p>By half Ranks, and by <hi>Converſion,</hi> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide the Squadrons into two Troops.</p>
               <p>In caſe you would reduce the Squadron, The Cammand is,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>By</hi> Converſion, <hi>the Squadron into one Troop, or the left Wing, Advance by Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In wheeling by <hi>Carocol,</hi> the words of Command are, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The right Wing to the left by</hi> Caracol, <hi>Face about to the Rear:</hi> Or it may be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed by half Ranks, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:64196:32"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>By Quarter Ranks, and by</hi> Carocol <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide the Squadron into three Troops.</hi> Then if you would reduce them, order Quarter Ranks and Squadrons into one Troop.</p>
               <p>If you are to be Commanded, the Volt, Face, or Facing about, obſerve it in this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Face about to the Right, Face to the Right by</hi> Controverſion, <hi>Face about to the Right by</hi> Carocol, <hi>Face about to the Left by half</hi> File, <hi>Face about to the Right and Left.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>In caſe in Hay you are to be drawn up, Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve this Order.</head>
                  <p>By half Ranks, To the Right and Left draw up, in <hi>Hay,</hi> To the Front; <hi>and if to be reduced again, the proceeding is thus, By</hi> Carocol, To the Right and Left. As you were. By half Ranks, and by <hi>Carocal,</hi> To the Right and Left. Draw up in <hi>Hay</hi> to the Rear. <hi>Reduction, here the Command is,</hi> To the Front. As you were. By half Ranks, to the Right and Left, draw up in <hi>Hay. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction,</hi> By <hi>Carocol,</hi> To the Right and Left. As you were. By <hi>Carocol,</hi> To <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he Right, draw up in <hi>Hay. Reduction,</hi> By <hi>Carocol,</hi> To the Left. As you were.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <pb n="60" facs="tcp:64196:33"/>
                  <head>The Order of cauſing Horſes to File off.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>File by Ranks on the right Wing, on the left Wing from the Squadron. File off by Ranks on the left Wing. Form the Squa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dron on the Right. File off by three Files on the Left Wing from the Squadron.</hi> Some, indeed, are for Filing off with whole Ranks; but the moſt Experience in this matter have found it moſt convenient to be done by Files, becauſe three Files make a Squadron, which a Rank does not.</p>
                  <p>The next material thing to be conſidered is, the Doublings being uſeful for the ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning any part of the Battle, as it ſhall be ſeen neceſſary, or required, conſiſting in theſe fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Heads. As to the General.</p>
                  <list>
                     <head>Front and Rear. Both Flank.</head>
                     <item>1. <hi>Doublings of Length.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. <hi>Doublings of Depth.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <p>But if you come to particulars, there are ſix ſorts of Doublings; as thus,</p>
                  <p>Firſt of Ranks, that is, when every Rank doubles into the odd, and if it happen that the odd Ranks are to double, then let the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy face to the Rear, and you need not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect any other words of Command.</p>
                  <pb n="61" facs="tcp:64196:33"/>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>Half Files.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. <hi>Bringers up,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Here they are ſaid to be doubled, at what time they double their Rear into the Front.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. In caſe of doubling, the Rear it muſt be done when the half Files double to the Rear.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Obſerve that the doubling of half Ranks muſt be by the one Rank doubling the other, and every doubling is done by the paſſing through by Counter-marches intire or diviſional doublings: And obſerve in the doubling of Ranks, that they are reduced by the doubling of Files, further noting that the doubling Files to any hand, by the doubling of Ranks to any hand, they are reduced.</p>
                  <p>In every Motion 'tis to be obſerved, that thoſe who are to double, muſt before they quit their places, Advance and Poiſe their Arms, and the Commands being performed, they are to conform to the ſame poſture as they obſerve thoſe to be in, to whom they double whatſoever the Poſture be.</p>
                  <p>If you go upon intire Doublings, they are to be performed by Order, as well in Rank as File, and in Diviſional Doublings, muſt be at open Order, as well in Rank as File,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:64196:34"/> obſerving your right hand man in all Moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
                  <p>If your purpoſe be to ſtrengthen a Batt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion in the Front, Rear, or Flanks by doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, it may be done as to the Front and Rear by intire Doublings, intire Wheelings, Diviſional Doublings, and Diviſional Wheel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings; and in the Flanks by Files, half Ranks, and Diviſional Wheelings.</p>
                  <p>In this caſe, the words of Command are, <hi>Ranks to the Right, Double. March, Ranks as you were. March. Ranks to the Left, Double March. Ranks as you were. March</hi> Obſerving i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> theſe matters a general Rule, That upon any doubling of Ranks, or half Files, notwithſtanding their turning to the contrary hand, they double on from the ground they double to. They (when they come to their own ground) muſt ever turn to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>and they double; and thereby they ſtand directly after their Leaders.</p>
                  <p>If you are for doubling of Files, that may be done in the ſame manner, holding in the ſame Order with the Reduction of doubled Ranks; and for the doubling Front, half Files, by the Rear half Files, the words of Command are, <hi>Half Files to the right Hand. Double your Front, March. Rear Half Files as you were, March. Rear half Files to the left hand, double your Front, March. Rear half Files, as you were, March.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="63" facs="tcp:64196:34"/>
                  <p>And again, if you would reduce, let the Rear half File ſtand without facing, till they are paſſed by the Front, half Files, then let them fall after their proper Leaders; but if by the Rear you intend to double the Front, half Files, the Rear half Files are to march exceeding ſlow, the body ſtanding ſtill, and in the half Files be curious to obſerve well the right hand Men, and in doubling of Rear, half Files by the Front, half Files with the Reduction: The words of Command are, <hi>Front, half Files, to the Right-about, Double your Rear, half F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>es. March.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In this caſe, the three Front Ranks, or Front half Files muſt turn to the Right about, paſſing on the right hand of the Rear; half Files doubling unto them, and then to face to the Left-about to their Leaders, without expecting the word of Command; and in caſe of Command, <hi>viz.</hi> Reduction, <hi>From Half Files as you were, March,</hi> the Front half Files are to March ſlowly three foot di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance from the right hand Man, directing more le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ward, which reducees them to their former Ground.</p>
                  <p>If you are deſirous to Exerciſe in Doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, obſerve the following Method,</p>
                  <p>Having drawn up the Battalion, and if it conſiſt of Musketiers, the Commander in Chief muſt give the word of Command, <hi>viz.</hi>
                     <pb n="64" facs="tcp:64196:35"/> 
                     <hi>Musketiers ſhoulder your Muskets;</hi> but if the Battalion be compoſed of ſingle Pikes, thoſe that are to march muſt be Commanded, <hi>viz. <hi>Ranks that are to double to the Right, Advance your Pikes. Ranks that are double to the Left, Advance your Pikes;</hi>
                     </hi> and this ought to be taken by the Pikes as a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Rule, when they form a Battalion of themſelves, always advancing when they are to double, fixing their Pikes upon the ground when they make a ſtand, but different from this in ſome kind, when the Battalion is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed of Musketiers only for the Command, then is what is required in the ordering Musketiers alone, and Pikes alone.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>To the right, double your Ranks in Front, March.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Here, if you would make your Doublings exactly true, then the Souldiers upon their parting from their left Feet, muſt come and place themſelves in the middle of the diſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the Ranks they double; and if the Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talion conſiſt of ſix Ranks in depth when they are to double by Ranks, either in Front or Rear, then muſt it looſe one Rank of the depth of ground, and the diſtances of the Ranks by that means ſhall become double to thoſe with whom they were before doubled; this being well obſerved, and you intend to reduce the Battalion, proceeding thus,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:64196:35"/> 
                     <hi>Ranks as you were.</hi> Then to double to the Left, ſay,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>To the Left double your Ranks.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>If you intend to double your Ranks by half Files, the Command muſt be, <hi>viz. <hi>To the Right by half Files. Double your Ranks in Front, March.</hi>
                     </hi> And the ſame words are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired to double the left by half Files, either in the Wings, or in the Rear; then to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce the Battalion, the Command is only, <hi>Ranks as you were.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>To double the Ranks in Front upon the Wings, ſo order it, that from the half File to the cloſe File, the Battalion cut, or di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide it ſelf in the half Ranks, then the half Ranks on the left hand muſt face to the left, and double upon the Wings of thoſe two that have not changed their ground.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:64196:36"/>
               <head>The manner of drawing up a Battalion, and the Officers taking their Stations for Parade, when they are to receive the King, or General, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>HEre the Battalion, or Regiment being drawn up in Exerciſe, the Ranks at twelve Feet diſtance, and the Files at three, the Musketiers ſloping, and carrying their Arms well, the Pikes muſt order their Pikes in a cloſe poſture to their Bodies, holding them near to their Heads, the butt ends to the Latchets of their Shoes: The Serjeants taking two, or one, on the right and left of every Rank at an equal diſtance, as the Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers are at in the File, but thoſe on the Rear muſt place themſelves at three paces from the laſt Rank of Souldiers, well ordering their Halberts, and having their Hats off, the Drums are to ſtand on the right, and the left even with the Front Rank of the Souldiers, and at the ſame diſtance one from the other. The <hi>Hoitboys</hi> are to be on the right of the Drums on the one ſide, and the Drums on the right on the other.</p>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <pb n="67" facs="tcp:64196:36"/>
                  <head>The Officers Poſts or Places.</head>
                  <p>Lieutenants to be divided equally at the head of the right and left Wings of Shot, the Enſigns to be at the head of the Pikes in an equal Line, each two paces diſtant from the Body; the Captains to be divided on each Wing, advanced two paces before the Lieutenants, the Commander in Chief ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted, none are to be before the Enſigns, and he to be two paces advanced beyond the Captains, unleſs it be when a Regiment makes but one Battalion, and the Preſence of the Colonel and Lieutenant Colonel be had, then the latter is to take his Poſt on the left hand of the former. The Major who muſt be on Horſe-back, is to place himſelf in a direct Line before the Serjeants on the right Angle, ſomewhat more advanced before the Line of the Captains, and the Aid Major being like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe mounted in the left Angle after the ſame manner.</p>
                  <p>If the King be to be received, then Pikes muſt be Advanced, and Muskets Shouldered, the ſame likewiſe to the Queen; but to all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers the Pikes are to Ordered.</p>
                  <p>If a Company of Granadiers belong to the Regiment, it muſt be drawn up on the right of the Battalion at three deep, about three paces being left between their Drums and thoſe of the Battalion.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <pb n="68" facs="tcp:64196:37"/>
                  <head>The Order and Manner of Salute.</head>
                  <p>As ſoon as it is obſerved the King ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches, the Drums muſt beat a March, and the Officers are to Salute in their Order as he paſſes by, keeping the Spear of their Pikes exactly with the proper Front, and not by any means turning their croſs ways.</p>
                  <p>The Salute being made, they without ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king a Leg, or Bowing, are immediately to pull off their Hats, keeping them off with their bodies upright, till the perſons to be Saluted are paſſed by.</p>
                  <p>The manner of the Enſign's Saluting is with their Colours at one Motion, bringing them near the ground directly before them, raiſing them altogether at one Motion, upon which they pull off their Hats as the former. The Serjeants are to ſtand with their Hats off, and their Halberts Ordered, facing the ſame way with the Battalion; and here it is to be noted, That if the Perſon to be Saluted goes round the Battalion, it muſt face as he moves, without altering the Poſts.</p>
                  <p>This muſt be obſerved upon the private review of a Battalion, but if it ſo happen, that it be to be done in the Field, and the Army drawn up each Battalion, muſt ſalute with Pikes and Muskets <hi>Charged.</hi> The Mus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ketiers upon the approach to be Shouldered,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:64196:37"/> and the Pikes Advanced, when the Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in Chief proceeds to give the Word, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Recover your Arms.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Upon this bring your Pikes and Muskets directly before you the butt ends of your Pikes in the Palms of your Hands, and the right Heel brought to the left Inſtep, and when the Drum firſt ſtrikes the March, you muſt Charge with Pikes and Muskets at one Motion, and keep your Arms in that poſture, till the perſon to be Saluted is paſſed by; up which theſe words of Command enſue.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Recover your Arms.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Poiſe your Muskets.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Shoulder your Muskets.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>At which time the Pikes are to be brought to the Advance, but in caſe of Marching the Salute is ſomewhat different.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>Of Marching and the Salute, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>In marching a Battalion, be ſure in the firſt place, to ſee the Files cloſe to the right or left in their marching Order, which is ſo much diſtant, as they can conveniently have the uſe of their Arms, without incumbering each other, and greater Bodies in this caſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire more diſtance than the leſſer, as half a Foot and more from the right hand Man, and ſo in Order to the reſt, when the Pikes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Advanced, and Muskets Shoulder'd. The words of Command are,</p>
                  <pb n="70" facs="tcp:64196:38"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Files cloſe to the Right,</hi> (or the Left.)</p>
                  <p>To your cloſe Order.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>March.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Then each man is to turn to the hand na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, and conſequently cloſes to the diſtances and hand mentioned; and when this is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, the next word of Command is,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>To your Leader.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Hereupon the Serjeants are to ſee the Ranks kept at their twelve large Feet di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, and being thus diſpoſed, if it march in a Body, the Lieutenants muſt be in the Rear, at the ſame diſtance they were in the Front from the Souldiers; the Serjeants that were in the Rear, taking care of the Flanks, that they keep even and well in Order, and upon the word <hi>March,</hi> they are in Front and Rear, to ſtep with their left Feet forward all at a time, ſetting them down together, marching very ſlowly, the Pikes marching equal with the Wings of Shot, not in the leaſt preſſing upon each other.</p>
                  <p>When the Body is marched as far as is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, then the Command to them muſt be,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Halt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>To the Right-about.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Drums beating a Retreat, the Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenants in the ſame Order and Method, lead them back to their Ground, as was before obſerved; and there again the word of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand is <hi>Halt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <list>
                     <pb n="71" facs="tcp:64196:38"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>viz.</hi> To the Left-about.</head>
                     <item>
                        <hi>To the Right-about.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>As you were.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <p>At this word, the Lieutenants muſt quit the Rear, and come to their ſtation in the Front, whilſt the Serjeants in the Flank who were removed from the Rear, take their places again.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>To March in three Diviſions, the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod and Order.</head>
               <p>IF you are to march a Battalion in three Diviſions, the Captains muſt divide the one half at the head of the firſt Diviſion of Shot, and the remaining half in the Rear of the laſt Diviſion: And again, one half of the Lieutenants in the Rear of the firſt Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion of ſhot, and the remainder at the heard of the laſt Diviſion of ſhot: The Colours marching at the head of the Pikes, which are to be Advanced, the Commandant in Chief marching two paces before the Rank of Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains at the head of the firſt Diviſion of Shot, the Captains and other Officers exactly keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the diſtance they were at firſt poſted at, when the Battalion was drawn up.</p>
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:64196:39"/>
               <p>The Officers that are appointed in this caſe, to march in the Rear of the Diviſion, are as they march off to fall after them; and the Serjeants that were poſted in the Rear, are to take care of the Pikes upon their march<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: As for the Drums, they are equally to be divided upon the Diviſion, marching be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the ſecond and third Ranks. The Granadiers marching about twenty Yards be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Battalion, the Equipage of the Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers of the Front muſt march ſomewhat on the left hand, between the Battalion and Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nadiers: The <hi>Hoitboys</hi> marching in the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle diſtance between the Colonel or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander in Chief, and the Granadiers.</p>
               <p>In marching, the Colonel and all the o- Officers muſt march with their Pikes under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand Comported, not ſuffering the Spear to deſcend too much, but keep it ſteady from ſwinging, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But if they have occaſion to Salute, they muſt, as they approach, Shoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der all together, that is, every Rank of Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers as they approach, carrying them level upon their Shoulders, performing the Salute, as if it was the Action but of one Man; not muſt the firſt Rank of Captains Salute, till the Colonel or Commander in Chief has per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed it, not ſtanding ſtill, or medning their Pace when they Salute.</p>
               <p>The Officers pulling off their Hats, as has been directed in the ſtanding Salute, or in a
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:64196:39"/> Battalion drawn up for a Review. The Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeants muſt march with their Halberts ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, the butt ends uppermoſt, always upon this occaſion marching with their Hats off, when thoſe that are to be Saluted paſs by, not any being to Salute the ſame Party more than once ſtanding, and once March<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
               <p>As for the Major, and the Aid-Major, they have not any fixed Poſt appointed in Marching, but are attending for Orders on the Colonel or Commander in Chief; and if an Enſign be abſent, a Pike-man, as he is qualified, claims the carrying or holding the Colours before either Serjeant or Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral.</p>
               <p>If it ſo happen, that a Battalion in the March be attacked, they muſt immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thereupon draw up, and face either the ſame way they March, or wheeling to the Right or Left, recovering thereby what Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages you ſhall ſee neceſſary.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="74" facs="tcp:64196:40"/>
               <head>How a Battalion ought to the Ordered if Attacked.</head>
               <p>IF you are marching in three Diviſions, or a greater number, then if you be Attack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and obliged to wheel to the Right, the firſt Wing of the Musketiers muſt draw up on the right of the Granadiers, and the Pikes on the right of the right Wing of Musketiers, whilſt the left Wing of the Musketiers takes the right hand of the Pikes, which is done with more Eaſe and Speed than by marching round the Rear.</p>
               <p>As ſoon as you prepare for Defence, or the Chief Commander is for drawing up the Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talion in the ſame Method, he gives the words of Command, that the Rear, half Files of Musketiers do double their Front to the Left in Marching, and upon the firſt Command to the Musketiers, to make ready, <hi>viz.</hi> (to be Cock'd and Gaurded) the Pike-men with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out expecting Command, are to Port their Pikes, and the Drums to beat a Preparative, whereby the Rear muſt take notice to draw up, and at the ſame time the Enſigns muſt give their Colours to the right hand Man of the reſpective Companies, who immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately muſt retire with them to the Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the Pikes; and the Enſigns taking
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:64196:40"/> the Souldiers Pikes, muſt march at the head of the Pikes: As for the Drums that before marched between the Ranks of the Muske<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiers; as likewiſe thoſe of the Granadiers, that are to be joyned with thoſe Drums that march with the Pikes; and the <hi>Hoitboys</hi> muſt joyn the Colours.</p>
               <p>When the Drums beat the Preparative, the firſt Diviſion excepted, every Diviſion is to march up with as much ſpeed as may be, not breaking or falling into any Diſorder, the firſt Diviſion marching ſlower, and not altering its former pace.</p>
               <p>The Ranks in marching muſt obſerve to cloſe forward at ſix foot, which muſt be well directed by the Serjeants who are to look to the Order.</p>
               <p>The Granadiers are to be divided into three parts, no part exceeding each other, and one of theſe parts muſt be with the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain at the head of the Pikes, about eight paces from the firſt Rank, and the other two parts on the right and left of the Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talion, when thoſe at the head of the Pikes are to receive the word of Command, <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent,</hi> and <hi>Fire,</hi> and the firſt Rank of Musketi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers are commanded to <hi>Kneel,</hi> and when they have fired, they muſt make ready their Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nadoes, and after the two other Ranks Fire, then are they to deliver their Granadoes, and place their Daggers in the Muzle of their
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:64196:41"/> Fire-Locks, and thoſe Granadiers placed on the right and left of the Battalion, are to make their Fire as the Musketiers Fire, <hi>viz</hi> The two laſt Ranks muſt fire with the Musketiers, and when they have ſo done, they muſt fix their Daggers in the Muzles of their Fire-Locks, then the Front of Granadiers muſt have their Granadoes ready, and likewiſe when the firſt Rank of Musketiers kneel, they muſt do the ſame, and when the two laſt Ranks have fired, they muſt ſtand up, and upon the fireing of the firſt Rank of Granadiers, they muſt deliver their Grana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>does, and fix their Daggers in the Muzles of their Fire-Locks as the others.</p>
               <p>Obſerve, that when the Adverſe Batta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion is ſo near, that the Granadoes may fall amongſt them, the Officers and Souldiers keeping their equal diſtance, the Commander in Chief gives the word to <hi>Halt,</hi> at which the Drums muſt ceaſe, and the Officers whoſe Poſt is at the Front, muſt Rank at the head of the Battalion two paces diſtant with their Pikes Ported, and four of the Serjeants that marched with the Pikes before they drew up, muſt draw up with them, <hi>viz.</hi> Two with the firſt Rank, and two with the laſt on the right and left of each Rank, and the remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Serjeants to be on the Ranks, and to be aſſiſting to the Officers in the Rear, who are to be thoſe Officers that took their march in
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:64196:41"/> the Rear before they were drawn up, and are to continue in the Rear of the Battalion, to take care of it, all except the eldeſt Captain who is to come up immediately to the head of the left Wing of Shot in the Front, and the Serjeants are to be very exact upon the Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talion, drawing up to order the Ranks at ſix foot diſtance, and the Files at the ſame, every Souldier for the better uſe of his Arms, and the paſſage of the Enemies Shot, to keep at leaſt a Foot from his right hand Man.</p>
               <p>When the Commander in Chief has given the word <hi>Halt,</hi> the next Command is, <hi>Ranks of Musketiers Kneel.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This is to be done by falling back with the right Legs, without moving the left, keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing your Muskets ſo low; that the two other Ranks without incommoding may fire over them, and upon the giving this word, the Rank of Officers poſted at the head of the Battalion, muſt fall at once into the Intervals behind the firſt Rank of Souldiers, taking care at the ſame time, that the Officers per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form their duties. The Officers having their Pikes in the poſture conformable to the Pike-men, and thoſe with the Musketiers muſt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve to kneel as the Musketiers do.</p>
               <p>When the word of Command is given for the firſt Rank to kneel, the other two Ranks of Musketiers are to cloſe forward, and in the ſame manner the five Ranks of Pike-men
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:64196:42"/> as they can with conveniency, and uſe their Arms without any word of Command.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Two laſt Ranks Preſent.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This muſt ever be obſerved to be done breaſt high, the firſt of the two ſtooping without any word of Command, and at the ſame word the Pikes are to Charge, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue Charged.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fire.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Retover your Arms.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>At which word of Command the foremoſt or Front Rank muſt ſtand up without expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing further Command, at the ſame time their Muskets being recovered ſtraight before them, Cockt and Gaurded.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Front Preſent.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fire.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Recover pour Arms.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Club your Muskets.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fall on.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This muſt be done with a Shout or Huzza, the Pikes continuing Charged, and the Drums beating another Preparative.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Halt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Upon this word given, the Drums muſt be ſilent, and now in caſe of a Reduction, it muſt be done by this order of Command, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Poiſe your Muskets.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Hereupon the Pikes muſt be recovered from the <hi>Charge;</hi> the Granadiers muſt take their Poſts, as before they were divided.</p>
               <pb n="79" facs="tcp:64196:42"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Shoulder your Muskets.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Pike-men at this word of Command, muſt bring their Pikes to their Thighs, to their Advance, the Rank of Officers Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing together before the head of the Batta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion two paces.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ranks open backward at twelve Foot di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>March.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rear half Files of Musketiers that doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to the Right-about, as you were.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>March.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Officers, Colours, Drums, and Hoitboys to your proper Poſts.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>March.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If it ſo happen that a Battalion be more than once to Fire in Exerciſe, then before you fall on, inſtead of Clubing your Muskets, when the firſt Fireing is over, the Musketiers as they March, muſt make Ready, and the Pike-men Port, noting by the way, that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very right-hand Man (being a Pike-man) of each Company muſt ever march with the Enſign's Pike.</p>
               <p>The Drums muſt beat the <hi>Preparative</hi> at what time the firſt Diviſion draws up, either in Battalion or ſingle Company, being the moſt ready way to give notice to the Rear to draw up likewiſe; when the <hi>Preparative</hi> is beat, the Pikes Shouldered are to Advance, except the Command be given to the Muske<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiers,
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:64196:43"/> to recover their Arms, and then the Pikes are to Port, but not otherways in drawing up, but at the Advance; neither muſt the Ranks cloſe forward, or mend their pace in Marching, but to draw up as at o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther times, except the Command be given to the Musketiers, to recover their Arms, or make Ready being the ſame poſture, then they are ever to march, as has been before directed.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>In Marching by <hi>Subdiviſion,</hi> what is to be obſerved.</head>
               <p>IF a long March be deſigned for a Battalion by <hi>Subdiviſion,</hi> the Files muſt be counted and ordered according to the wideneſs or narrowneſs of the ways they are to March, poſting one half of the Captains at the head of the firſt <hi>Subdiviſion</hi> of Shot, and the other in the Rear of the laſt, dividing the Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants to every <hi>Subdiviſion</hi> of Shot for their better care of them, the Colours being like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe divided to march at the head of every <hi>Subdiviſion</hi> of Pikes, and the Serjeants are always to march on the Flanks, never leading or bringing up a Diviſion, except Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:64196:43"/> and thoſe Serjeants that are placed at the Rere of a Battalion, when drawn up, are ever to take care of the Pikes, in Marching; and in this way of Marching they are to March ſhouldering, in Files, but not in ſuch Order as to joſtle, or incroach upon one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; and although at ſometimes it may fall out that more Men may be in one Rank than in another, yet the Spaces muſt not be Left but they are to file in Marching ſhoulder to ſhoulder, the Captains and Officers ever to March with their Pikes under-hand, unleſs it be when they paſs by a General Officer, or advance before a Guard, which they are to Relieve, or off the Parade, in which Caſes they are to ſhoulder.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>Defiles,</hi> their Management.</head>
               <p>A <hi>Defile,</hi> properly ſo termed, is a mirey Lane, or difficult Place of Paſſage; if it happen withall to be narrow, and to make good the Paſſage you would draw up as ſoon as you have paſſed it in order, then make the Ranks Files, and if the Right, the Right-hand man is to File firſt, and the reſt of his Rank muſt follow him; then are they to Rank again as they were, which proves
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:64196:44"/> more advantagious than Files fileing; for this Reaſon, <hi>viz.</hi> Becauſe it preſently makes a Front to the Enemy; and in caſe of great Ranks, they may File two a Breaſt, begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning with the outermoſt File-Leaders, and if the ſpace will admit, that is in large <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>files,</hi> the Commander may make a Front by Drawing off, as appears beſt to his Diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>Wheeling,</hi> what it is, and how to b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> obſerved, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>WHeeling</hi> is a Motion in Military Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe which, by turning, brings the Head of a Battalion to the Flank ground, which is extremely neceſſary, if the Wing of a Battalion be attacked, or when you ſee it advantagious to attack the Enemy in the Flank; and on many other occaſions as the advantage, or diſadvantage of War offers. But to the purpoſe:</p>
               <p>The Battalion drawn up, the Officer in chief gives the Word of Command, <hi>March,</hi> and when the Battalion wheels upon the firſt Head of the right hand File, then it wheels to the Right, and when it do's the like upon the Left, it wheels to the Left.</p>
               <pb n="83" facs="tcp:64196:44"/>
               <p>A Quarter <hi>Wheeling</hi> is termed the firſt <hi>Wheeling,</hi> as it happens when they take a Compaſs to poſſeſs their own, or the Ground left by another Battalion; and in all Whee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings ſuch compaſſes of Ground muſt be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken as that they leave no gap, nor preſs each other out; and to avoid this, every Man muſt take notice of his diſtance at File, the Word of Command being given to Wheel, and then if you are to Wheel to the Right be ſure to keep that diſtance from your right-hand Man, the Ranks taking great notice of their Leaders, cloſing very quick to the Left in the Rear, obſerving to do the like to the Right, if the Battalion wheel to the Left.</p>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>The manner of <hi>Wheeling</hi> a Battalion, or Body, when they March in Diviſion.</head>
                  <p>The Battalion being upon the March, and commanded to Wheel, when it is ſo ſo ordered to the Right, the right hand Man keeps his ground, only turning upon his heel, whilſt the left hand Man moves about with a ſwift pace, till he makes an even Line with the right-hand Man, and the Word be given to Stand, the ſecond Rank obſerving not to begin to Wheel till they have taken the ground of the firſt; by which means every Rank is to March ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſively
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:64196:45"/> forward up to their Leader's ground before they attempt to wheel, for therein lyes the dexterity of this way of Wheeling.</p>
                  <p>The Soldiers before they offer to Wheel muſt take notice of that hand in Marching to which they are to Wheel, for as the Right hand Man is to be noted upon the March when they Wheel to the left; ſo on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary the Left-hand Men when they are to Wheel to the Left. If the Service requires Wheeling in ſingle Ranks, obſerve</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>The Manner of Wheeling in ſingle Ranks.</head>
                  <p>When it is requiſite for the Service to wheel in ſingle Ranks for lining or guar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding. The Words of Command are, <hi>viz.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ranks to the Right,</hi> or if to the Left, then</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ranks to the Left-hand Wheel, March.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Right or Left-hand Man, to which the Wheeling is made, being to keep his ground, only turning till the Line comes direct, the reſt, being all to Wheel together in one Rank, and at the VVord of Command <hi>March,</hi> the Colours muſt wheel in before the Ranks, the Drums taking their Places on the right and left of the Ranks, as muſt the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeants obſerving that they be cloſed to the right or left, without leaving any unſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Spaces; and to Reduce again, obſerve the following Order.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="85" facs="tcp:64196:45"/>
               <head>The manner of <hi>Reduction.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IN doing this, the left-hand Man of each Rank muſt ſtand, and keeping his Ground only turn about to the Left, and at the word <hi>March</hi> the reſt that compoſe the Rank muſt wheel to their places.</p>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>The manner of Wheeling backwards by Half Ranks.</head>
                  <p>Here you muſt obſerve there muſt as near as poſſible be an equal number of Men in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Rank, the right and left-hand man of each Rank ſtanding firm on his ground, and turn only to the hand named, the words of Command being, <hi>viz.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>By half Ranks wheel to the right and left backwards, March.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Whereupon the Battalion opens the half Ranks, ſeparating and falling back to the right and left-hand Men, which leaves an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tervale, and forms two Ranks oppoſite to each other, the Officers and Colours divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in the ſame manner, taking their Poſts and Ranging before the Souldiers to make a Guard, the Serjeants and Drums placing themſelves equally on the right and left: This being obſerved, the manner of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:64196:46"/> is by theſe Words of Command, <hi>viz.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>By half Ranks to the right and left in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward. Form your Ranks as you were. March.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Here the half Ranks are to wheel from the right and the left, and cloſe the inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>val, by which means they become whole Ranks; for having wheeled inward at the word <hi>March,</hi> they are no more half Ranks but whole Ranks in a Marching order. In caſe of Cloſings and Openings there are di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers words of Command required, <hi>viz.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ranks cloſe forward to Order, <hi>viz.</hi>
                     </hi> (three foot) <hi>March.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ranks cloſe forward to cloſe Order, <hi>viz.</hi>
                     </hi> (a foot and half) <hi>March.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ranks open backward to Order, <hi>viz.</hi>
                     </hi> (three foot) <hi>March.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ranks open backward to open Order, <hi>viz.</hi>
                     </hi> (ſix foot) <hi>March,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ranks open backward to a doubling diſtance, <hi>viz.</hi>
                     </hi> (12 foot) <hi>March.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In this manner of proceeding to open back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the Ranks muſt fall backward in Order, without changing the Aſpect, having ever regard to their Leaders and right-hand Men.</p>
                  <p>The further Words of Command are, <hi>viz.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Files cloſe to the Right, March.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Files cloſe to the Left, March.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Files cloſe to the Centre, March.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Files open to the Right, March.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Files open to the Left March.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="87" facs="tcp:64196:46"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Files open from the Centre, March.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>By the Files opening to the Centre, is meant their facing from the Centre, and if there happen to be an odd File, that remains and is properly termed the Centre File.</p>
                  <p>When Files are to open to the right, or to the left, they muſt keep their ſtation with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Changing in any manner, till the word <hi>March</hi> be uttered; whereupon they are to face to the hand named, taking their diſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces commanded, each from his Leader. In all Openings, as has been ſaid, the contrary Man muſt be obſerved; if the Command be to open to the right, the ſecond File from the right muſt by ſhort ſteps firſt take its diſtance, ſuffering the Leader to paſs as far as it is commanded, before you move, the reſt of the Files in their turn and order ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving to do the ſame; as for the left-hand File it is not to move; in all Openings they are to move directly forward with a ſlow pace.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>Thus the young Souldier may his Duty Read,</l>
                     <l>But now to greater Things we muſt proceed;</l>
                     <l>The Ratling Drum and Trumpet calls us on</l>
                     <l>A Souldier's Work you know is ſeldom done</l>
                     <l>But ever Travels with the glorious Sun.</l>
                  </q>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="88" facs="tcp:64196:47"/>
               <head>A further Conſideration of <hi>Doublings,</hi> Relating to <hi>Foot,</hi> &amp;c. and their <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>RAnks to the Right double, March.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Ranks as you were, March.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Ranks to the Left, March.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>Ranks as you were, March.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In caſe of doubling the Ranks, thoſe that are to do ſo, muſt obſerve their right-hand men, and move, as they move, beginning to move with the Foot next the hand then named, and ſo to come into Order, this doubling the even Ranks, muſt be obſerv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d to double into the odd, &amp; when the odd Ranks are to double, you muſt face the Body to the Rear, and the like words of Command will perform it, or you may further proceed, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Odd Ranks that ſtood to the Right-about, Double the even Ranks.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>The Reduction of Ranks, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>Thoſe Ranks that double, muſt face firſt to the contrary hand, and then with the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary foot bring themſelves to the former Ground, but not to move in the leaſt, till the word <hi>March</hi> be given, and this is held upon all doublings of Ranks, and half Ranks, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:64196:47"/> the contrary hand is to be turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to, they muſt double on to the Ground they double to, yet coming to their proper Ground, they there muſt turn to the hand they doubled, and thereby they are brought directly to their Leaders. And in the like manner Files are doubled, remaining much the ſame with the Reduction of doubled Ranks.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>The manner of doubling Front, half Files, by half Files of the Rear.</head>
                  <p>The words of Command in this caſe are,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Half Files to the Right-hand Double your Front. March.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Rear half Files, As you were. March.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Rear haal Files, to the left hand double your Front. March.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Rear half Files, As you were. March.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>If this happen upon the March, the Rear half Files muſt then move into the Front by a very ſwift motion, the Front half Files at the ſame time continuing there, each obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the right-hand Man.</p>
                  <p>In caſe of <hi>Reduction,</hi> the Rear half Files muſt not face about, but ſtand ſtill till the Front half Files are paſſed, and then fall in, and follow the proper Leaders, but if the occaſion require the Front half Files to be doubled by the Rear, the Rear half Files muſt march a ſoftly pace, obſerving their right-hand
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:64196:48"/> men, ſo that all the Ranks may double at one time.</p>
                  <p>Obſerve in <hi>Reducement,</hi> as it is in the doubling of ſingle Ranks, that no man muſt move till the word of Command, <hi>March</hi> be given, upon which they turn all together up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the contrary hand they doubled on, and when they come up to their own Ground, they muſt turn to the hand they doubled to.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>Rear half Files doubled by the Front half Files.</head>
                  <p>Here the words of Command are, <hi>viz.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Front half Files to the Right-about, double your Rear half Files.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This word of Command given, the three Front Ranks, or three half Files muſt turn to the Right-about, and going on the right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand of their Fellowers, or the Rear half Files, they muſt double into them, and when they have doubled, face to the Left-about to their Leader, without expecting any word of Command.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>The manner of Reduction</head>
                  <p>The words of Command are,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Front half Files, as you were.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>March.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Whereupon the half Files muſt march ſlowly, keeping at three foot from their
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:64196:48"/> right-hand Men, by which means they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline to the left, and are brought directly up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their former Ground; and it is only doing thus, and obſerving the contrary hand in doubling to the Left.</p>
                  <p>Now it remains that ſomewhat more par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly then has been ſaid of the ſeveral manners of Fireings be laid down, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>The manner of Fireing to the Front.</head>
                  <p>When the Souldiers are to Fire, and keep their Ground, 'tis expedient that the Body be made cloſe as well as in Rank as File, as will ſtand conveniently with the uſe of Arms, and hereupon, Command muſt be given, <hi>viz.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Musketiers make Ready all.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Then they are to have their Arms ſtraight before them ready Cockt and Gaurded, and the Pikes being Ported, they muſt charge when the Musketiers Preſent, and then en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue the further words of Command, <hi>viz.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The five firſt Ranks kneel.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Rear Ranks Preſent.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Fire.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Fifth Rank ſtand up.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Preſent.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Fire.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Fourth Rank ſtand up.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Preſent.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="92" facs="tcp:64196:49"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Fire.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In this manner the reſt muſt be Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, &amp; when they have fired, they are to Charge again, and make themſelves in readineſs, to expect the next word of Command, and this Order of Fireing may be performed by two or three Ranks at a time, the firſt kneeling, the ſecond ſtooping, and the third ſtanding up.</p>
                  <p>In fireing to gain ground, obſerve this Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, The Battalion marching, he that is to give the word of Command proceeds thus,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Firſt Ranks of Musketiers make ready.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Halt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Upon this the intire Battalion muſt Halt, then he is to Command the Musketiers of the firſt Rank,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>To Preſent.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Fire.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And as ſoon as they have fired, they muſt recover their Arms, not expecting any word of Command, and with a ſwift pace File off to the Right and Left into the Rear, obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ever when the firſt Rank Preſents, the next Rank is to make Ready, and as the firſt files off, the next muſt make good the Front, Battalion marching, and every Rank to fire in this Order, and at the preſenting of every Rank, the Pikes without Command.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <pb n="93" facs="tcp:64196:49"/>
                  <head>The manner of Fireing to the Front, Retreating.</head>
                  <p>If the Enemy preſs your Battalion in Front, and you cannot make good your Ground, you may to prevent their preſſing on Fire, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treating in ſingle Ranks in the ſame manner, as when you are to gain Ground, except, (after the fireing of every Rank, and their having filed off to the Right and Left into the Rear) inſtead of the next Ranks advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing to make good the Front of the Pikes, the Pikes muſt make their Retreat to the Musketiers, who muſt keep their Ground till the Pikes make an even Front equal with them, and the reſt of the Ranks in their Fireing and Retreating, are to obſerve this Method.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>The manner of Fireing in the Flank.</head>
                  <p>If a Battalion be upon the March, and is conſtrained by reaſon of the preſſing of the Enemy to Fire, to both Flanks it is to be thus performed,</p>
                  <p>Keep the Ranks at ſix foot diſtance, and the intervals of that diſtance muſt be carefully obſerved between the Muskets and Pikes in their Diviſions, and this muſt be done by cauſing the Musketiers to incline to the right and left upon every fireing to the Flanks.</p>
                  <pb n="94" facs="tcp:64196:50"/>
                  <p>The words of Command are, <hi>viz.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>To the right and left hand, Files of Mus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ketiers, make Ready.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Which they muſt do, and keep along with the Body, not facing to the Flanks, till they are commanded to Preſent; and when they have fired, they are to face to the Rear; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thereupon lead a thwart very quick by the Serjeants, and ſo up between their own Diviſions and the Pikes, and as ſoon as ever the next Flank Files Preſent, thoſe that ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed or ſupport them, are to make Ready with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out expecting the word of Command, as is many other caſes has been inſtanced, keeping a long with the Body till they are bid Preſent and this Order muſt be obſerved, till all the Files have fired, each man upon fireing fall<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing back with his right Leg, in caſe of fireing to the Rear, which many times ſtands in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtead, eſpecially upon being Charged by a greater number, or upon a Retreat; you muſt obſerve the following Order.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>The manner of Fireing in the Rear.</head>
                  <p>The words of Command directing this way of Fireing are firſt,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Rear Ranks of Musketiers make Ready.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>By which is underſtood Cocking and Guarding.</p>
                  <pb n="95" facs="tcp:64196:50"/>
                  <p>Then <hi>Preſent.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Fire.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Upon theſe words, the Souldiers muſt turn <hi>to the Right-about,</hi> caſting their left Legs backwards, then Preſent and Fire, which done, they muſt recover their Arms without any word of Command, marching up into the Front, and there taking their Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and note, that as ſoon as the firſt Rank is bid Preſent, the next is to make Ready without Command, but muſt not face to the Rear till Commanded to Preſent; and when the firſt Rank is bid to Preſent, the Pikes muſt march till ſuch time as the Rear of the Pikes are even with the next Rank of Mus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ketiers that have made Ready, by which means room will be left in the Front, for that Rank that fires, to bring themſelves up even with the firſt Rank of Pikes, every Rank being to do the like by the ſame Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The manner of Fireing the <hi>Street-way.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THis Fireing is generally made to defend againſt Horſe that attempt to Charge in the Front, when the Pikes are few, then the Rear half Files of Pikes muſt double the
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:64196:51"/> Front; upon this Command, <hi>viz. <hi>Rear half Files of Pikes to the Right. Double your Front.</hi>
                  </hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>March.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Musketiers to the Right about, March.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Musketiers being clear of the Pikes, the following Commands are to be given.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Musketiers face to the Right and Left in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>March.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Upon this Command, they are to joyn the Center of the Pikes, and the Commandan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> proceeds, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Face to your Leader.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Hereupon the care of the Officers muſt b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to obſerve the Shot, and the Pikes equall<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Wing, the former keeping no more diſtance from the latter then to give ſpace for the Enſigns, Drums and Hoitboys to com<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> between, then the Captains are to take place in the firſt Ranks of the Pikes, and the Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenants with the Musketiers; and according as the Body is bigger or leſſer, one or more of the Serjeants muſt ſee the two firſt Ranks of Musketiers to face to the right or left, and when the Command is given by the Chief Commandant, <hi>viz. <hi>Port your Pikes.</hi>
                  </hi> The Musketiers of the two firſt Ranks muſt make Ready, and at the word <hi>March,</hi> the two firſt Ranks are to be brought up by the Serjeants to the right or left according as it is ordered,
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:64196:51"/> who by two and two ſiting up, they thwart under the Pikes, and there they are to face to the proper Front, without expecting any VVord of Command, and to make two Ranks, and that ſome are may be ever reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, 'tis moſt expedient to fire but one Rank at a time, the ſecond being cock'd or guarded to ſtand either of them as near to the Pikes as the Management of their Arms will per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit, then the VVord is to be given, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt Ranks of Musketiers kneel.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Upon which they muſt fall-back with their right legs, keeping their left fixed, their arms-upright before them, their left hands even with their mouths; then the further word of Command is given, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Preſent.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fire.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Immediately upon fireing they are to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover their Arms without expecting the word of Command, and ſo file off on the contrary hand they advanced on, with as much ſpeed as they can, the Serjeants lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding them cloſe by the Body unto the Rear, placing them there, in their proper Files.</p>
               <p>The Musketiers being commanded to <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent</hi> the Pikes muſt port very low without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other word, and in the ſame Order to raiſe their Pikes as ſoon as they have fired to their proper heighth, the ſub-altern Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers always minding, that the next Rank of
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:64196:52"/> Musketiers be ready at the Angle to make their March under the Pikes, inſtead of the ſecond Rank which is to take the Place of the firſt when the firſt Rank has fired.</p>
               <p>In this manner of fireing, if the ſtreet to be defended be very broad then a ſpace, or interval muſt be made, over and above the paſſage on the flanks, ſufficient for two Men a breaſt, which will prevent the Horſe from making any advantagious Attack.</p>
               <p>To reduce this Order, the Words of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand are, <hi>viz. <hi>Musketiers face to the right and left outward, March;</hi>
                  </hi> and as ſoon as they are quit the farther, Command is given, <hi>viz. <hi>Musketiers to your proper Front March.</hi>
                  </hi>
               </p>
               <p>This they, muſt obſerve to do till ſuch time as they are even with the firſt Rank of Pikes, and then the Officers, Drums, Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours, and Hoitboys muſt take their proper Poſts.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="99" facs="tcp:64196:52"/>
               <head>Of the hollow Square, and the manner of forming it by Words of Command.</head>
               <p>IF you proceed to this, the Battalion muſt be drawn up in Ranks, at Twelve Foot diſtance, the Files being at three, then the Muskets ſhouldered, and the Pikes advanced the Words of Command enſue, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Colours, Drums, and Hoit-boys to the Centre of the Pikes, March.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ranks cloſe forward to Order, March.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Three outward Files of Pikes on the Right and Left, double your Files to the Right and Left inwards, March.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Half Files of Musketiers to the left-hand double your Front, March.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Files cloſe all to the Right, to your cloſe Order, March.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>To your Leader. Pikes face ſquare. Pikes cloſe forward to the Front. Left Wing of Musketiers to the Right about. Both Wings of Muketiers March. Halt. Musketiers Face to the Left, March. Halt. Face to your proper Front, all Officers and Serjeants take your Poſts, March. Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nadiers take your Poſts in the Angles, March. Face ſquare. Musketiers make ready.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="100" facs="tcp:64196:53"/>
               <p>At this VVord the Pikes muſt be ported very low, when the Musketiers preſent, and the next VVord is, <hi>Firſt Rank kneel,</hi> which muſt be done in ſuch a manner that the two laſt Ranks may advantageouſly Fire over. Then again, <hi>The two laſt Ranks preſent, Fire.</hi> Having fired, the next is, <hi>Recover your Arms,</hi> upon which the firſt Rank is to ſtand up with their Muskets recovered, rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy cock'd and guarded, whereupon the two Ranks that have fired take the opportunity to Load again, and theſe VVords of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand enſue, <hi>viz. <hi>Front Ranks preſent, Fire,</hi>
                  </hi> which done, the Commandant proceeds, <hi>viz. <hi>Recover your Arms,</hi>
                  </hi> and hereupon the Pike<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men recover from their Port, then again <hi>To your Leader, March, Halt, Face Square,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Theſe being performed after the ſame Order, they may March, and fire to every Front, noting that when they are hid to Face to their Leader, it muſt be to the Commandant in chief, wherever he takes his Station; but in facing to the proper Front it muſt be done to the Front of the Battalion, as it was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore; it was formed into this manner of Figure.</p>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <pb n="101" facs="tcp:64196:53"/>
                  <head>Words of Command uſed to reduce this Form.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Battalion being faced to the proper Front, the Commander in chief proceeds, <hi>viz.</hi>
                     </hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Granadiers take your Poſts on the right of the Battalion, March.</p>
                  <p>The Right and Left of each Wing of Musketiers Face to the Right and Left out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, March. Halt.</p>
                  <p>The three Files of Pikes of the Right and Left that doubled as you were, March.</p>
                  <p>Musketiers Face to the Right, March. Halt.</p>
                  <p>To your Leader.</p>
                  <p>Rere half files of Musketiers that doubled to the Right about, as you were, March.</p>
                  <p>Ranks open backward to Twelve Foot, March, Colours, Drums, and Hoitboys to your former Poſts, March.</p>
                  <p>Files cloſe to the Right, to cloſe Order, March. To your Leader.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="102" facs="tcp:64196:54"/>
               <head>Things proper to be obſerved by a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander, being in an Enemies Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>HE muſt be carefull to obſerve the ſitua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Place, and gain as good In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligence of the Enemy as he can, and if he Command a Troop of Horſe, he muſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware of skirting the ſide of a Wood, for fear of an Ambuſh, the ſtrength of Horſe, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting in the open Country, as that of the Foot do's in a VVood; for the Enemy is all ways to be expected to take advantage; it is therefore dangerous for a Troop of Horſe, by reaſon it may be fallen upon before it can get to any ſecure Poſt.</p>
               <p>An Officer of Foot marching through an incloſed VVoody Country, muſt avoid, if he can, marching in the middle of a Plain, or too near a VVood, by which means if the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy approach he will have time to conſider what courſe to take; and if he be attacked by Horſe, then ought he to retreat unto the Wood, Skirmiſhing to make it good; for if he get into it, the Horſe will not attack him there; but if he has to deal with Foot, and obſerves himſelf the weakeſt, he muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain the laſt Defile, or narrow Poſt, and drawing up in Battalia, diſpute it, till he
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:64196:54"/> can better ſecure himſelf; and the like is to be obſerved by the Horſe, if overmuch preſſed; wherefore it is good for a Commander to take ſpecial notice of the places he paſſes through, ſending his Scouts before him to diſcover the Enemy, and ſearch the Places where Ambuſhes are ſuſpected; for although it be in a Village, there may be a Party of the Enemy there, who will ſuffer the Scouts to paſs by, and conceal themſelves till they ſee an opportunity to ſet upon the main Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy.</p>
               <p>When an Officer is arrived where he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends to Encamp he ought to Draw up his Men, and having ſet his Guards, he may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit them to take ſome eaſe, by alighting from their Horſes, if it be Horſe, or if Foot, to repoſe themſelves, always facing towards the Town or Place poſſeſſed, or ſuſpected to be poſſeſſed by the Enemy, having, if poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, a Defile in the Front and Rear, or ſome other ſecurity; to prevent ſurprize, the Scouts ought to be ſent out from one half hour to another, and when day appears they may venture farther into the Country, and if there be no convenient Town, or Place, the beſt way, if two or three days March in the Enemies Country, is to lye in a Wood when it has been well ſearched, to prevent an Ambuſh; nor muſt an Officer ſuffer his Men to ſtraggle, though he be near a Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:64196:55"/> Town; for it may ſo fall out that a Party may lye hid, who taking that advantage may fall upon him, and rout him, though a leſſer number; for there it is the Enemy moſt commonly lays Ambuſcades, thinking, as it often happens, that by a Confidence of Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity they ſhall find Men negligent and diſordered.</p>
               <p>When at any time the VVord is required of a Party you meet, it is generally given by the weakeſt, however it ought not light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be credited, nor the Souldiers to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn their Arms till the Officer be aſſured whether they are Friends or Foes; for many times a Deſerter may betray the Word to the Enemy, and he make an advantage of it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Conſiderations in Marching an Army through an Enemy's Country, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IF the War be carried into the Enemies Country, to beſiege or relieve any place whether the Enemy keep the Field or be beaten, Caution ought to be had, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally in Caſe of the former, nor is it other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe to be believed but he may Rally again; wherefore it behoves the General to March
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:64196:55"/> cloſe ſo that the Army may be in a Condition to open its paſſage to do which it ought to be divided into little Bodies the Cavalry placed upon the Wings in Front and Rear of the Bodies, the Infantry, marching in the middle, in a groſs Battalion, the Artillary upon one ſide guarded by an experienced Regiment, and ſo it happens that an Army never undergoes more difficulty than in an incloſed Country full of VVoods, and Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers eſpecially if in an Enemies Territories where ſo many difficulties will ariſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Of marching in a Woody-Country, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THE moſt probable Advice that can be given in this caſe, is to ſend the Pio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neers ſupported by Horſe and Foot, to cut open ways of more eaſie paſſage, fill up the Ditches, and lay over Bridges, and to do what elſe is required, getting by Scouts, and commanded Parties; what Intelligence there can be had, and the General not truſting al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together to others, muſt be careful to inform himſelf, and if he meet with a Bridge, or difficult Paſs defended by Curtains, Baſtions, or any other Heights; the Engineers having
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:64196:56"/> well viewed it, it will be convenient to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tach a Party, to try whether the River be fordable, and theſe being Horſe, may carry over each a Foot-man behind them, which will more facilitate the Paſſage, but if there be an Eminence to defend it, on which Canon are placed, then he may raiſe a croſs Battery in the moſt advantagious place, and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to diſmount their Cannon; but if the Entry be fortified with a Baſtion, then a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded Party of reſolute Men muſt be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tached to attaque it, which muſt be done ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dainly, and with much Vigour, for that daunts the Enemy, when on the other hand, delay encourages them to ſtand out.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>How a General ought to behave himſelf when he meets with Caſtles and ſtrong Fortreſſes in his March.</head>
               <p>TO overcome theſe Difficulties, the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genier and Marſhal <hi>De Camp</hi> muſt look out the moſt advantageous ground to place the Cannon for Battery, and obſerve the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies Cannon how they bear, as alſo their Sally, Ports, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And if he deſigns to make himſelf Maſter of them, he ought to take the
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:64196:56"/> moſt convenient Poſts, not only to annoy them, but to prevent their being Succoured, and raiſe a convenient Battery on the weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt ſide, or that which by the Approbation of the Engenier lies moſt open to the Attaque, cauſing the ground to be diſtributed for an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>campment, as the Quarter Maſter General ſhall think fit, and if the place to be forced prove ſtrong, Earth muſt be caſt up to ſecure the Approaches from the Cannon or Shot, running Lines Travers-wiſe, and Indenting, ſo that they cannot bear upon thoſe that ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach, till they come to the breach made by the Batteries, or undermining any part, where they can charge their Mine, and throw down the Wall, but if it be not of extraordinary Strength, requiring a formal Siege, then a reſolute Party may be detached from the main Body, ſupported by others with Scaling Ladders, Faggots, Spades, Shovels; Pick-Axes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to fill up a Trench or Ditch, whilſt the Armed Bands attempt to force the Gates with Petrades, or the like Engins, or ſcale the Walls, ever maintaining and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king good their Poſts; but in this caſe the Methods are various, as the Service required, offers it ſelf more or leſs difficult; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we preſume not to give exact Rules for what frequently alters.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="108" facs="tcp:64196:57"/>
               <head>Of <hi>Encampments,</hi> and how they are uſually Managed.</head>
               <p>THough the manner of Incamping fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently is attended with ſome Varia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; yet to give the young Souldiers an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſight in theſe Affairs will not be unneceſſary as to what has been lately practiſed.</p>
               <p>When an Army, or any great Body is to Encamp, it is uſually diſpoſed in Lines with a Reſerve, concluding the ground at the ſame time to be convenient for the ſo recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving them, and if the Lines are but two, there ought to be 300 paces diſtance between them at a yard, the Pace and the Squadrons of Horſe have for every one five and thirty paces of ground allowed, and the like ſpace between the one and the other, that ſo with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out diſorder, they may march out if there be any occaſion to Ingage.</p>
               <p>As for the Infantry, if they Incamp ſix deep, they muſt have 80 paces at three Foot, the pace allowed, or more if the Scituation of the ground require it, and between the Squadrons of Horſe and Battalions of Foot, the Line muſt be forty or fifty paces diſtant. The Artillary ought to be placed upon the firſt Line of Infantry at ſuch Advantage as
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:64196:57"/> may beſt annoy the Enemy if they come to make any Aattaque.</p>
               <p>The Baggage and Ammunition take their place between the ſecond Line and the Body of the Reſerve on the right Hand, and the Proviſions on the Left, or near the Tent of the Commiſſary General of Proviſions.</p>
               <p>The Quarter Maſter and Serjeants as well Horſe as Foot, are to pitch their Tents in the Front, or Head of their Squadrons or Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talions, and the other Officers Tents behind: The principal <hi>Corps du Gaurd,</hi> and the Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding place claims to be at the head of the Camp, where the Arms, Enſigns, and Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours are Lodged.</p>
               <p>The Poſts of the Horſe are on the Wings, and the Foot take their Station in the middle, and to every Squadron, conſiſting of three Troops, and fifty Men in a Troop, fifty pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces are allowed, and every Battalion conſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of 16 Companies, and 50 Men in each Company ought to haue 100 paces for their Incampment.</p>
               <p>As for the Dragoons, they are not En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>camped in the Body of the Army, but have their Camp a little ſeparate at the Head or Wings, to which the greateſt danger ſeems to threaten, as being the out-gaurd for the Army, and each Regiment ought to have a Gaurd at the head of their Camp, and the Major General for that day is to take care to
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:64196:58"/> place the great Gaurd in a convenient place, at a diſtance from off the Army towards any expected Danger, which may diſcover any approach before it come too near, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by prevent any Surprize, for Caution is to be uſed where Danger is not, as well as where it is.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Remarks upon the Encamping of Horſe.</head>
               <p>IN Encamping a Troop, if it conſiſt of 100 Men, they ought to have 70 Foot in Front allowed them, and 200 in depth, eight Foot in breadth, and 12 in depth muſt be account<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to two Horſe-men to make their Hutts or Barques, and the Men and Horſes are to be Lodged in two Ranks, the Horſes heads ſtanding towards the Hutts of their Owners, yet between the Hutts and Stables there ought to be an Interval of eight Foot: The Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains Tent to be at the head of the Barques of his Troop, poſſeſſing the whole Front, and between the Lodging of the Captain and the Troop, there muſt be the ſpace of 20 Foot, a Lane of 10 Foot muſt be likewiſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Stables, that the Horſes may be brought out without incumbering each other,
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:64196:58"/> and behind the Troop, the Sutlers ought to place themſelves at about 20 Foot diſtance, and if any conſiderable number of Troops Encamp together, then 20 Foot diſtance is allowed between Troop and Troop, or more, as the commodiouſneſs of the ground will allow.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The manner of the Incampment of Foot.</head>
               <p>A Hundred paces is commonly allowed for the Incampment of a Battalion of Foot, divided by the Quarter Maſter into ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Stations, he allowing for each Hutt or Lodging a Square of 7 Foot, 12. Foot to the By-ſtreet, and 15. Foot to the great Street, and two Foot diſtance between Hutt and Hutt, every Company compoſed of fifty Men, ought to have ten Hutts; and the Kitchin for dreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Proviſion, ought to be juſt over againſt the Hutts at 12 Foot diſtance, the length of the Kitchen 12 Foot, and the breadth 8, ſtanding about 30 paces from the Captains Tents, and 40 paces between the Tents of the Subalternate Officers and the Captaine, the remaining ground being for the Encamp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Field Officers, and this Captains Equipage, the Hutts of the Serjeants are to
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:64196:59"/> be at the head of the Souldiers, opening to the Front, the Suttlers to Encamp behind the Tents of the Officers at a convenient di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, &amp; about 30 paces are allowed between one Battalion and another; the Colonels, Field-Officers, and Staff-Officers, Tents ought to be in the Center of the Battalion behind the Captains Tents, and the Pikes to be at 18 Foot diſtance from the Hutts, the Muskets to ſtand the like diſtance, and the Drums and Colours to be placed within the hollow of the Pikes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Things worthy to be obſerved in Relation to <hi>Garriſons.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THoſe Officers that take place in a Garriſon are uſually a Governour, a Lieutenant Governour, a Major, Aid-Major, and Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains of the Gates.</p>
               <p>The Governour above others is obliged in this caſe to have a care of the Place, and ſee that there be no wrong done to the Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants, and furthermore he is to appoint the Guard Rounds, and Patrolls, to give the Word each Evening, viſit the Poſts, keep the Officers and Soldiers in ſuch Order that
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:64196:59"/> their Duty be performed, obſerving that fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent Parties go abroad to get Intelligence, and thereby prevent ſurprize; and in the Governour's Abſence the Lieutenant Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour has the ſame Charge upon him, and commands with the like Authority.</p>
               <p>The Major's Care is to ſee the Guards mounted, the Poſts and Rounds aſſigned, he Orders the Sentinels, and goes every Eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to receive the Word from the Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, giving it about to the Quarter-Maſter and Serjeants upon the Place of Arms, and likewiſe goes his Rounds; the Major alſo viſits the Corps of Guards, and obſerves that the Soldier's Arms are well placed, and in good Order, ordering the neceſſary Ammuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to be diſtributed amongſt them, he takes care of the Gates being ſhut and opened, and is accountable to the Governour of what paſſes, and gives him a Relation thereof, and indeed the Officers that are in Gariſon are to be obedient to the Governour or Commander in chief, and not to ſtir thence, without leave in Writing.</p>
               <p>The Captains of the Gate are to go mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and evening to the Governour's Houſe to receive the Keys, that they may open and ſhut them, and frequently there is in the Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon, if it be in a Frontire-Town more e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially, a Commiſſary of the Artillery or Store keeper, whoſe care it is to keep a
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:64196:60"/> Reckoning of the Ammunition, and to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtribute it according to the Governour's Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and always one Gunner is to be upon the Guard, at the Batteries. There ought to be likewiſe a Commiſſary of the Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, and if there be any ſuſpicion of an Enemy, ſome of the Garriſon ought always to be at the Gate, to obſerve Strangers that go in and out, and the Centinels are to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer no Carts or Waggons to ſtand or ſtop upon the Bridge, or under the Gate, and the Inn-keepers, and others, muſt give an Account to the Major every night what Strangers they Lodge.</p>
               <p>As for the exact time of Mounting the Guards it cannot be ſet down by reaſon ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny vary, being ſet ſooner, and others later, as pleaſes the Governour, but the frequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt time is about Two in the afternoon; and whilſt the Drums give them that notice the Serjeants and Corporals caſt Lots at the Major's Houſe for the Poſts and Rounds, which are writ down in a Regiſter to that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent; then they return to their Companions, who aſſemble before the Captain's Quarters, and if only detached Men mount, and not whole Companies, they are Lead by the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeants, the Drums beating the while, as far as the place of Arms, and when the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tachments are drawn thither, and formed in a Readineſs to Mount the Guards, the Major
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:64196:60"/> or Aid-Major, makes the Captains, even to the Serjeants, draw Lots for their Poſts and Rounds, always obſerving in the weakeſt Places to poſt the ſtrongeſt Guard with skil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Officers, and not till the Officers have taken their Poſts do's the Major order the Main Guard, or Guard of Arms to March off: then he cauſes thoſe of the Gate and Baſtions to do the like, and after them, thoſe that were without, and during the time the Guard is mounting thoſe Officers who are to be Relieved put their Men in a poſture of Arms, and Draw off from the Guard, po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting themſelves at the Head of their Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, over-againſt thoſe that are to take their Places, and deliver to them whatever Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders there are, whilſt the other Corporals do the like to the Corporals that are come on, and thoſe that are Relieved being Drawn up at the Place of Arms, they are there diſmiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, in order to refreſh themſelves.</p>
               <p>Thoſe Officers that have Mounted the Guard proceed thereupon to Command the Souldiers to ſet down their Arms, the Pikes at that time being advanced, and the Muske<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiers ſhouldered, which is done upon theſe Words of Command, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Recover your Arms.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ranks file off by Diviſion to the Right and Left. March.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Set down your Arms in good Order.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="116" facs="tcp:64196:61"/>
               <p>This done, the Corporals upon the Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers ſetting down their Arms, receive Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders to be carefull in all things that they may be in a Readineſs to prevent Danger, or Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize; and here the out-Sentinels upon the approach of any Stranger, whether Horſe or Foot, are to make him ſtand, and call their Corporal, who is to give notice of it to the Officer, and he to ſend him to the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour's Houſe, with a Guard, to know his Buſineſs, and if the Centinels diſcover any Troops, though at a great diſtance, they are to give notice to the Main-Guard, and the Officers are to make the Barriers faſt, and draw up the Bridges, ſuffering none to paſs unleſs an Order be brought from the Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, by the Major, or Aid-Major.</p>
               <p>There is in all, or moſt Garriſons, a Bell to give notice to thoſe that are abroad to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pair home a little before the time of the Gates being ſhut, and then the Keys are fetched from the Governour, and returned again, ſo that none can paſs after the Gates are ſhut; and then one half of the Guards Draw off upon the Rampart to paſs that night in the Corps of Guard in the Baſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons or Curtains and whilſt ſome Soldiers are ordered by the Corporal to fetch Fire and Candle, the VVords are received by the Serjeants at the Place of Arms, and then it is carried to the Officers, and diſperſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:64196:61"/> amongſt the Corporals, and after that, none, whether Towns-men or Strangers are to be upon the Ramparts, without giving an Account of themſelves, eſpecially when the Taptooe is beaten; and the Major him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, when he goes the Rounds is received by the Officers of the Guards by their Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral, attended by two Muketiers giving the Word but once, <hi>viz.</hi> at his Round-Major, but when the Governour or Commander in chief is received upon the Rounds he may require the VVord as many times as he thinks fit; all other Rounds are obliged to give the VVord, and the Corporal receives it with his drawn Sword at the Breaſt of the Party, and where there is the leaſt thing ſuſpected in a Garriſon, the Rounds go frequently as every quarter of an hour, that the Ramparts may not be unprovided, and care is taken to know who neglects; and thus Rounds are made with Light; wherefore at the Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach of it, the Centinel muſt demand VVho comes there? with ſuch an audible Voice that it may be heard by the next Guard, and he that approaches muſt reply, or may be in peril; for the Centinel is not to let him come within his Arms, and the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer is generally the Round, the Round Major, or the Governour's Round being to be received not by the Centinel but the Corporal, who is called forth for that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe,
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:64196:62"/> and he is to bid him that has the Word Advance, which upon coming forth he gives him in his Ear ſo ſoftly that it cannot be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver-heard; but if the Word be wrong, the Officer of the Guard is to have notice, and the Party to be ſecured, if he ſees occaſion; and although in the night-time it is obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved that the Centinels ſtand with their Pikes charged, and reſt their Muskets upon the paſſing by of the Rounds, yet in the day-time it is the contrary; for then the Pikes are ordered, and the Muskets ſhoulde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. As for the out Corps of Guard they paſs the Rounds about the covered Ways; but there is no Word required of them, they being only to liſten, and give notice if any thing happens.</p>
               <p>As for the Patrolls they are made in the Street by a Serjeant, commanding about ſix Soldiers of the Main-guard, and then the Soldiers are to be in their Quarters, and all publick Houſes within the Garriſon to ſhut up their Doors; and at any time when the Alarm is rung all the Soldiers are to haſten and preſent themſelves before their Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain's Quarters, in order to his Leading them to the Poſts aſſigned by the Major; and when day appears the Reveille is beat, and the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eys are fetched again from the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour, and the Soldiers are commanded off the Romparts, and drawn in two Ranks
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:64196:62"/> with their Muskets preſented, till the Gates are opened, and a detached Party muſt be ſent out into the Suburbs, adjacent Villages, and narrow ways, the Bridge being drawn up after their going out till they return and bring News the Coaſt is clear, thereupon the Bridges are let down; then the out Centries being placed, the Keys are carried back to the Governour, and the Souldiers are commanded to ſet down their Arms, though where there are any conſiderable number of Horſe in Garriſon, it is their Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs to go out upon Parties, and ſee that the Roads are clear, and every Officer is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countable for his Poſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> All Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, or Commanders in chief, ſhould have their Doors guarded by a Centinel, or a greater number according to their Quality in Command. Theſe are the chief things, and indeed the moſt material, and ought to be carefully obſerved; for it has ſometimes appeared that the ſafety of a Kingdom has depended upon a ſtrong Fortreſs.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="120" facs="tcp:64196:63"/>
               <head>A Survey of War-like <hi>Fortification,</hi> and what is to be obſerved in Sieges, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IF a Town be defended by Out-works, a Ditch, or Mote Baſtions, Flankers, Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains, or Counter-mures, and the Garriſon be ſtrong, it was the old Way to build Forts at advantagious Places, but now they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed in a Siege, by making Trenches, rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Batteries, Mining and gaining Lodg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, which indeed is the quicker way, and the moſt ſecure from the Cannon of the Town. The beſt Fortification is held to be built Octangular, by which means the force of the Cannon is much abated; for the points of the Angle ſlaunt the ſhot, or if it make a breach in the hollow Cavity, yet the Angles ſerve as Flankers on either ſide to hinder the Approaches of the Beſiegers, ſo that it has happened when there has been a Breach wide enough to enter they durſt not Attempt it; though indeed the manner of Fortification is various throughout <hi>Europe,</hi> yet the late Models have been indifferently u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niform; and in caſe a Town be well forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, and an Army comes to Beſiege it, a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious View muſt be taken, and the true Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:64196:63"/> of the Ground, as well as the Scituation of the Place, enquired into, with the Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the Garriſon, and eſpecially the Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, Conduct, and Reputation of him that Commands; for as it is in an Army ſo it is in a Town, a valiant Governour, whoſe Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage is carried on with Prudence, will better defend it with a ſmall Garriſon, than ſome with a very powerful one, as the famous City of <hi>London-Derry</hi> has inſtanced to the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal Honour of her worthy Governour, Mr. <hi>G. Walker</hi> whoſe Name ſhall live in ſpite of all that Malice can deviſe; <hi>Vienna</hi> likewiſe, under the brave <hi>Staremberg,</hi> in the year 1683. held out till Relieved againſt an Army of 120000 <hi>Turks,</hi> being the Flower of the <hi>Ot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toman</hi> Empire, and yet neither of theſe Cities had any thing conſiderable to truſt to in their Fortifications: But to return.</p>
               <p>The place being viewed, and the ground ordered to be broke, the Pioneers once ſet on work, muſt make ſuch places or Lodgings that thoſe who enter them may be able to ſuccour their Fellows againſt any vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Sally of the Beſieged, having Iſſues and Paſſages for paſſing and re-paſſing as the beſt advantage ſhall require.</p>
               <p>Having made theſe Advances, the Artille<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry muſt be planted upon Batteries raiſed with Earth, and ſtaked with Timber, ſecured with Gabions or Baskets filled with Earth, or
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:64196:64"/> elſe the Engineers cannot be ſecured from the Fire of the Town, Wool-packs were former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly uſed on this occaſion, and are not altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther laid aſide in the preſent management of Sieges, planting your Batteries ſomething a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlant, that the Cannon if recoyling, may the eaſilier be brought up again, and always in this there is one Battery bigger than the reſt, called the Royal Battery, which generally fronts the Town beſieged, and is frequently raiſed as high as the Walls, and theſe Batte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries muſt labour to diſmount the Cannon of the beſieged, as well as batter the Walls, for thereby the Enterpriſe will be facilitated, but many times the Flankers are covered in a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner by the Counterſcarp, which muſt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon be laid open, or poſſeſſed by the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiegers, to gain a more uninterrupted Acceſs, and if the beſieged Parly, and ſend out to make terms, Hoſtilities ought to ceaſe till thoſe that came out are returned, unleſs the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiegers will refuſe to hearken to any Parly which is not often obſerved, unleſs the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter be carried ſo far, that the breaches are laid open, and there is no way or means for a longer Defence; then inſtead of gaining Conditions, they are forced to ſurrender up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Diſcretion.</p>
               <p>If by Battery, Mining, throwing Bombs, or a perpetual tiring the Enemy, the Town is ſaultable, and a general Storm be intended,
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:64196:64"/> it muſt however be the General's care as much as in him is to keep his intentions from the beſieged, but pretending one thing ſuddenly change, the Order into another, for by it the Enemy is accuſed, and the Souldiers Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits are kept up; this Rule was obſerved by the Duke of <hi>Lorain</hi> in taking of <hi>Buda,</hi> and proved very ſucceſsful, as it has done in the like upon other occaſion.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The Court Martial, or Council of War, what is to be conſidered therein.</head>
               <p>IT is neceſſary the young Souldiers ſhould have ſome inſight in this Affair, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent his ignorantly incurring Danger, and in this Caſe in an Army, or Incampment, the Council of War meet at the General's Tent, or Quarters, and to this are called the Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant-Generals, the Major-Generals, the Brigadiers, as likewiſe the Collonels, and Commanders of Bodies, where it is requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite, or that the Matter concerns their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giment.</p>
               <p>There are private Court-Martials, or Councils of War, frequently held in Garri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and theſe may be held at the Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour's Houſe, or in any other convenient
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:64196:65"/> place, as the Governour ſhall appoint; or if it be in a Camp it may be at the Collonel's Tent, and he thereupon is to ſend notice to the Captains of his Regiment to be preſent; thoſe whoſe buſineſs it is to be there being aſſembled, the Collonel, or Governour, or whoſe Right it is to be Preſident, takes place at the upper end of the Table, and the Captains in their Degree, and if there be no Judge-Advocate, or he be abſent, the Town-Major, Aid-Major, or Quarter-Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, diſcharges that Office, and accordingly takes his place at the lower end of the Table. As for the Lieutenants, Sub-Lieutenants, and Enſigns, they have Priviledge to be there but only as Spectators with their Hats off, and if the Matter be of conſequence, after it is opened by the Preſident, the youngeſt Officers gives firſt his Opinion, and ſo the reſt in Order, the Preſident being the laſt, and being put all in Writing, the Matter happens conform to the plurality of Votes and then is to be ſigned by the Preſident; if the matter is to be judged of by this Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil or Court, then the Party accuſed is brought before them, and being informed of what he ſtands accuſed, the Queſtions proper to the matter of his Accuſations are asked him, and then he has Liberty to reply, as in caſe of civil Judicature, when being withdrawn in the cuſtody of the Marſhal
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:64196:65"/> who is the Goaler of this Court, the proof againſt him is conſidered, and every one gives his opinion upon his Conſcience, and he ſtands or falls by the plurality of Voices, and being called in and made acquainted with what has been determined, the Sentence is pronounced by the Preſident in the name of the Court, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and if he be guilty 'tis the buſineſs of the Provoſt Martial to ſee it put in Execution, and if the Puniſhment be pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick, the Regiment ought to be drawn up Spectators, as a warning to them in offend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but a Souldier for the Honour of the Profeſſion is not to undergo any infamous Puniſhment before he be degraded of his Arms, and his Coat in publick ſtrip'd off, and to frame this Court, there muſt be no leſs than Seaven, the Preſident being one, many times for want of a ſufficient number of Superiour Officers, Inferiour Officers are admitted, but not often.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="126" facs="tcp:64196:66"/>
               <head>Of divers Figures in Battel-Array, or for Fireing, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THere are various Figures wherein an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my or a Body of Men may be drawn up, beſides theſe we have named, wherefore for the ſatisfaction of the more curious, and for the greater variety, it will be convenient to incert them by way of Proſpect, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If you would draw up a croſs Battle in the following Figure, you may do it with a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Company, or as many as you pleaſe, and to bring them into form: The words of Command are, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The firſt two Ranks wheel your Front in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the midſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The two laſt Ranks wheel your Rear into the midſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe words being given, the next Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand muſt be,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The reſt of the Body Face to the right and left, March.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The March muſt be continued till the Rear of the four Diviſions make an even Hollow that may be ſquare, after that, the Commander muſt go into the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle, and give theſe words of Command, <hi>viz. <hi>To the Center face all,</hi>
                  </hi> by which means
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:64196:66"/> he may give them directions what to do, and then proceed further to ſay, <hi>Face all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to the Right,</hi> which makes the croſs Battle.</p>
               <p>Of the two Diviſions, one after the other, Then <hi>Face all to the proper Front.</hi> So you have all your Musketires in the midſt flanked with Pikes, Then <hi>Musketiers Face.</hi>
               </p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>cross-shaped battle array, in which each arm of the cross is labeled Front S.</figDesc>
                  <head>The Croſs Battel.</head>
               </figure>
               <p>
                  <hi>Face to the right and left outward. Pikes face to the right and left inward, paſs through and interchange ground.</hi> So is your Body reduced to its firſt Front and Order.</p>
               <pb n="128" facs="tcp:64196:67"/>
               <p>If you would fire upon this Figure, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider there are two ways in general, and of theſe firſt it is to be noted when the Musketiers give Fire, thereupon placing themſelves in the Rear of their own Diviſion, the next Rank is after they have Fired, place themſelves in the Rear of the Pikes.</p>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>To Reduce the Croſs Battle.</head>
                  <p>The Officers in the middle muſt give the Command, <hi>viz. <hi>Face all to the Centre:</hi>
                     </hi> And then further proceed to Command thoſe Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions that were Flankers, <hi>viz. <hi>Cloſe to your Order.</hi>
                     </hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The four fronted Battle, called the <hi>Plyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thium,</hi> how to frame it by Command.</head>
               <p>TO order this, the Command muſt be, <hi>viz. <hi>Half Files of Pikes Face to the Rear.</hi>
                  </hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>March.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This they muſt obſerve till clear of the Ranks of the Musketiers, and then the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand is,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Half Files of Musketiers Face to the Right and Left.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>March.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="129" facs="tcp:64196:67"/>
               <p>This muſt be done in marching between the Diviſions of Pikes, then the further word is,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Left half Ranks of the firſt Diviſion of Musketiers Face to the Right, and March between the Rear Diviſion of Pikes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In this caſe it is noted, that the Muske<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiers muſt be in the middſt, and the Pikes as Flankers.</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>the plynthium, a four-fronted battle array</figDesc>
                  <head>The Figure of the four Fronted Battle, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </head>
               </figure>
               <p>To Fire upon this Figure, the Musketiers muſt do it in Rank, and after Fireing, wheel off to the Right, making their paſſage through the intervals and placing themſelves in the Rear of their own Diviſion ſucceſſively,
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:64196:68"/> maintaining the ſame Ground, or if you would bring the Musketiers to the Angles, and reduce the Pikes to the middle, then muſt the Musketiers take place on the Flanks when you make the Figure.</p>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>To reduce this Figure.</head>
                  <p>The whole Body is commanded to Face to the proper Front: And then,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Musketiers in the Rear March up on the Left of the Musketiers in the Front.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Musketiers in the Flank Face inward, and cloſe your Diviſion.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Theſe Commands given, cauſe the Pikes to march up, taking their places directly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter their Leaders, and by that means they will be brought into a ſollid ſquare: The Commands are,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Musketiers Face to the Right and Left inward.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Pikes Face inward interchanging Ground.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="131" facs="tcp:64196:68"/>
               <head>The Hollow Fronted Croſs Battle, how to form it.</head>
               <p>THE Files in this caſe being eight Men in depth, the words of Command are thus to to be given,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The two firſt Ranks wheel your Front in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the midſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Two laſt Ranks wheel your Rear into the midſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The reſt Face to the Right and Left.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>March.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Here they muſt move untill they have made the Croſs, then the Musketiers muſt Flank the Pikes, as for example in the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Figure.</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>the "hollow fronted cross" battle array</figDesc>
                  <p>Proper Front.</p>
                  <p>Front of the Right Flank.</p>
                  <p>Front of the Rear.</p>
                  <p>Front of the left Flank.</p>
               </figure>
               <pb n="132" facs="tcp:64196:69"/>
               <p>If you come to Fire in this Figure, it may be done every way as at Front, Rear and Flanks, the Fire made, they muſt wheel off by Diviſion, and take their ſtations in the Rear of their own Diviſion, moving for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward into the Leader's Ground, that the form of the Figure may not be altered, and when the ſecond Fire is given, the Pikes muſt move leiſurely up, Porting as they Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance, till they make an even Front with the Musketiers, the ſecond Fireing being made, thoſe that fired are to wheel, and place themſelves in the Rear of that Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Pikes which they Flanked, which or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, all the Ranks muſt obſerve upon Fire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and by the Pikes, Charging and Re-ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancing, the Figure will be preſerved, and the Reducement may be obſerved in what is directed for the Reducement of the croſs Battel.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>How to frame the hollow Square with Angles when required to be guarded with Pikes.</head>
               <p>IN this caſe the Pikes being Advanced, the Command muſt be,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pikes cloſe your Diviſions before the Mus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ketiers.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="133" facs="tcp:64196:69"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pikes face all to the Right.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>upon this, they muſt Advance and move into the ſpace between the Angles of the Musketiers, by which means the following Figure will be formed, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>"hollow square with angles" battle array</figDesc>
                  <head>Front.</head>
               </figure>
               <pb n="134" facs="tcp:64196:70"/>
               <p>In fireing upon this Figure, you have your choice to fire either to the Rear, Front, or Flank, as many Ranks as will ſtand with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniency, who upon fireing muſt wheel off and keep the ground, or upon fireing, they may retire into the Figure and charge for a ſecond fireing.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>How to form the Quintuple hollow Square, <hi>&amp;c</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IN forming the following Figure, the Mus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ketiers having made Ready, and taken their ſtation in the middle, make the hollow Front croſs Battel by wheeling the Front of the two firſt Ranks into the middle, which done, the Rear of the two laſt Ranks muſt be wheeled into the midſt likewiſe, then the reſt of the Body muſt Face to the Right, and the Left and March, till they have formed a Square, whereupon the words of Command are,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Face to the Front, Rear and Flanks.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This done, the Pikes in the Front of the Musketiers muſt be Commanded, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Open to the Right and Left.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="135" facs="tcp:64196:70"/>
               <p>Upon this, the laſt Rank of Pikes muſt be even with the firſt Rank of Musketiers, and then theſe words of Command follow, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Two firſt Ranks of Musketiers of each Diviſion move forward clear of the Pikes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This done, the following Figure will be produced.</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>"quintuple hollow square" battle array</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <pb n="136" facs="tcp:64196:71"/>
               <p>In fireing upon this Figure, the Command is,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Musketiers in the midſt, cloſe to the Front, Rear, and Flanks.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fire,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>The Musketiers ought upon the firſt fire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to make good their Ground, the ſecond time fireing over, they muſt Rank even with the Pikes, and upon the third fireing, the Pikes muſt move ſomewhat forward, and the Musketiers looſe Ground, by which means a hollow Fronted Croſs is formed, and the Pikes muſt Port and Charge in the Angles, whilſt the Fire is made by the Musketiers.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The form of a hollow ſquare Battle im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paled with Shot.</head>
               <p>TO bring this into Figure and Order, the Serjeants muſt draw forth the odd Files on the right Flanks as well Muskets as Pikes, then give Command to the odd Files of the left Flank, Pikes and Musketiers, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Face to the Rear.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This muſt be obſerved in wheeling to the left Croſs, the Rear following, the Bringers up, then the Command to the reſt of the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy is<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </p>
               <pb n="137" facs="tcp:64196:71"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cloſe to the Right and Left outward.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This muſt be till the Rear Angles of each Diviſion be in oppoſition to each other, then the Command is,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>All Face to the Center.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Face all about to the Right,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By this means the following Figure is formed.</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>hollow square battle array</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <p>Noe, In theſe Figures, that C ſtands for Commander in Chief, L for Lieutenant, E
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:64196:72"/> for Enſign, S for Serjeant, and D for Drums, P are Pikes, and M Muskets.</p>
               <p>To Fire upon this Figure, when the Ranks of Musketiers have preſented and fired, they are to wheel off to the right and left through the Intervals, that ſo they may be made in the middle of each Diviſion, as appears in the Figure, and then they muſt place them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in the Rear of their own Diviſion, the next Rank moving into their Ground, or if any urgency require it, the Musketiers ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving fired, they may wheel off and take their ſtation in the Rear of their following Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Pikes, which Diviſion is to move for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward and maintain the Musketiers Ground.</p>
               <p>If you would reduce the Order, the word of Command to the whole Body is,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Face to the left Angles of the Front Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Upon this, they muſt March and even their Ranks, and ſtraighten their Files, upon which the half Files muſt double their Ranks to the left forwards, and the firſt Order will be regained.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="139" facs="tcp:64196:72"/>
               <head>Directions or general Obſervation in giving Battel.</head>
               <p>THough there can no certain Rule be aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribed where the Contingencies are va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, yet it has been obſerved by experienced Commanders, that Rules are neceſſary, wherefore a Commander muſt avoid en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaging againſt his Will, as much as in him lies, and take the happy moment to charge the Enemy, when he ſees an active Livelineſs, and ſprightly Vigour in his Souldiers, cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the moſt advantageous Ground accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the quality and number of his Men, ſheltering for fear of being encloſed, one of the Wings or Flanks to a place ſtrong, either by Nature or Art, and bring on the Diviſions of Horſe and Foot at their ordinary diſtance, placing the beſt Regiments of Horſe and Foot on the Wings; if the Enemies out front you on the contrary Wing, it is requiſite, then the contrary Wing muſt march leiſurely, and give the Charge as ſoon as ever the Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non is playing, and if your Diviſion of Horſe out-flank the Enemy, then may they wheel and charge them in the Flank at the ſame time, the reſt of the Horſe are charging in the Front, and likewiſe it may be done on both
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:64196:73"/> Wings if they exceed the Enemy, but if your Horſe be few in number, the beſt way is to keep near the Foot, the better to be ſhelter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed if need require by the favour of their Shot, or there is a further ſecurity, to draw up on the outermoſt Flank of the Wing of Horſe that is out-flanked, the Rear Guard of Horſe of the ſame Wing; and this muſt be done with ſpeed, or if it happen that your Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of Horſe do front the Enemies Foot, when you are out-flanked by their Horſe, then ought the Officers to draw off the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion and place them on the outermoſt Flanks of that Wing which is out-flanked, and in all matters of War Diligence and Expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is wonderfully available with caution not to let your Councils be diſcovered to the Enemy, which if you ſuſpect to be done by any Diſſerter or Priſoner taken, it will be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite to change them ſo far as is convenient.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:64196:74"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:64196:74"/>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>depiction of a siege</figDesc>
                     <l>A Prospect of Grim war you here behold,</l>
                     <l>Sieges and Battles wee In this unfold.</l>
                     <l>To Show In peace what dreadfull Mars dos teach.</l>
                     <l>By which you may fames higest glory Reach.</l>
                  </figure>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="part">
            <pb n="141" facs="tcp:64196:74"/>
            <head>THE SECOND PART: OR THE <hi>Expert Engenier:</hi> Being the <hi>ART of G<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>NNERY,</hi> AND Making Fire-Works for WAR and other Matters. Serving as a SUPPLEMENT To the foregoing TREATISE.</head>
            <p>AS great Ordnance are an eſſential part of War, ſo it will not be a miſs, but altogether convenient to give the Practitioner in Enginry a proſpect of thoſe Affairs that muſt unavoidably concern him,
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:64196:75"/> &amp; therefore he that would improve himſelf in this kind either by Land or Sea, muſt firſt be careful in knowing what Materials are requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite, as alſo to be skilled in Geometry and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rithmatick, the better to know what meaſures to take on ſundry occaſions that vary in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</p>
            <p>And to this purpoſe, the Gunner muſt ever have Rammers, Scoups, Ladles, Sheep-skins with the Wool on, to ſpunge or clear the Piece; as likewiſe Canvas or fine Paſt-board to make Cartridges for the Powder, when the Piece is hot with often diſcharging, leaſt the Powder being put in loſe, it fire of it ſelf, he muſt have ſpare Wheels, and Axel-trees, leaſt any ſhould break in the way, and ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay the March of an Army, which frequently happens to its great detrement, ſhot he muſt have of fuch ſizes as the Pieces will bear even to the full of the Calliber, leaſt forcibly rat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling againſt it flaw the Piece; he muſt like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe have caſe Shot to break the Front of an Enemy, open a Paſſage, on clear a Deck when borded; likewiſe hand Spikes, Budg, Barrels, Baskets to carry Shot, Match, well Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Linſtocks, Torches, dark Lanthorns, and Compaſſes to meaſure the Piece and Shot, and to prevent breaking the Charge, muſt be proportioned according to the thinneſt Met<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal of the Piece, and in this caſe, the Charge being put in with your Scoup; if you are to
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:64196:75"/> Fire upon a Line, or under Mettal, you muſt be ſure to clap in a good wad after it, and ram it down, or elſe the hollowneſs of the Powder may chance to burſt the Piece, not only to the defeating your Deſign, but to the killing and wounding many Perſons near it, which has but too ſadly happned by careleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; and to move or travers your Piece, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide, hand Spikes or Leavers, you muſt have Crows of Iron, Coins of Wood to lay it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove or under Mettal, taking care to know the depth of the Chamber of the Piece, that the Charge may be agreeable, for if the Shot be to light, or too heavy for the Charge, it will never anſwer your expectation.</p>
            <p>Of Artillary, there are ſeveral kinds, <hi>viz.</hi> the Falconet, the Baſilick, the Rabinet, the Falcon, the Minnion, the ordinary Minnion, the Sacker, the loweſt ſort, the ordinary Sacker, the Sacker of the elder make, the loweſt De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miculverin, the eldeſt ſort of Demeculverin, the ordinary Demiculverin, Culverin of the beſt ſize, ordinary Culverin, Culverin of the largeſt ſize, loweſt Demicannon, ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Demicannon, Demicannon of the great ſize, Cannon Royal, or whole Cannon, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the biggeſt of all Ordnance.</p>
            <p>According to the bigneſs and weights of the ſeveral Pieces, they muſt be charged both with Powder and Shot, and if we ſuppoſe a Piece to be in length eight Foot, and that this Piece
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:64196:76"/> weighs 1500 Pounds, having four Inches Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amiter in the Bore, and you would know how much it requires, take notice that it requires four pound of Powder to carry a Shot of ſixteen Pound 160 paces at five large Feet to the pace, and do Execution, unleſs the Piece be defective, by reaſon of Flaws or Honi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>combs within, and to try the firſt of theſe as ſoon as ever the Piece is diſcharged, ſtop the Muzzle of it, and the Touch-hole, and if there be any Flaws that come through, you will perceive the Smoak work through them, this is to be known likewiſe by an Iron Hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpike, which will cauſe the Piece to jar, if the Flaws are conſiderable.</p>
            <p>The Honicombs are certain ſpungineſs or defects of the Mettal in caſting, which may be perceived by reflecting the Light of a Looking-Glaſs held againſt the Sun into the Mouth of the Piece, or putting in a peice of Candle on a long Cleft-ſtick.</p>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="145" facs="tcp:64196:76"/>
               <head>The Terms of deſcribing a Piece and Shot, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THE outward Ring of the Breech is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the Caſcabel Deck, that Ring next the Touch-hole is called the Baſe Ring, and that place between the Touch-hole &amp; the next Ring, is called her Chamber or Charging Cillinder, the next Ring is the Ramforce Ring, the third the Tronion or Ballance Ring, and that next the Muzzle is called the Cornice Ring, and the uttermoſt Extremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty is the Muzzle, the hollow is called the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liber, the top the Superficies, and the whole length the Chaſe, ſo that he that will be a Gunner, muſt have theſe diſtinctions at his Fingers ends as ready as a Sailer has the points of the Compaſs.</p>
               <p>As for the Shot uſed, it is generally Iron, but ſometimes Lead, and for want of theſe Stone, and theſe muſt be conſidered accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to their weight and bigneſs, for there is a diſproportion, if we conſider the equality of their Weight, and this not being well ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, may be of great hindrance in haſty Exterprizes, and the proportions are theſe.</p>
               <p>Between Lead and Iron ſix to nine, by which it is obſerved, that a Shot of ſix Pounds Iron, is as big as nine Pounds Lead, and the
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:64196:77"/> proportion between Iron and Stone is three to eight, ſo that there is eighty to thirty, for a Shot of Stone of thirty Pound is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proportionable in bigneſs to an Iron Shot of eighty Pounds; and in this manner you may gueſs of any kind.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>How to make <hi>Cartridges,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
               <p>IN caſe a Piece is very hot by Exerciſe, and will not endure the Powder, then a Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tridge is neceſſary to make them; you muſt have a Rowler of Wood to the bigneſs of your Piece, on which you muſt role Paſt-board or Paper, paſting it as you role, that it may lie firm and ſmooth, then having dried the caſes, fill them with Powder, and choak them at both ends with a ſmall Cord, or you may ſtop the ends with Flax, and put it into your Piece, forcing it with the Rammer into the charging Celinder, then with a ſharp Iron bore it at the Touch-hole and Prime.</p>
               <p>If you would ſhoot red hot Bullets as many times, it is done at Sieges to fire Houſes, you muſt when you have rammed down your Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tridge, force a green Turf upon it, and then ſling in the Shot, this way has been common,
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:64196:77"/> eſpecially at Sea, but ſince Bombs, Hand-Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nades, Stink-pots, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> haue been in uſe; it is not often practiſed.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Obſervations in Ballancing a Piece.</head>
               <p>YOU muſt ever obſerve in Marching, that the Carriages are proportioned to the Piece, to prevent overthrowing, or break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, ſo that to ſet them true, one and a half of the length of the Cellinder or Chamber ſhould be the length of the Carriage-Stock, and the depth of four Diamiters of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cave of the Bore in the middle, but at that part next the ground, about the proportion of the Diameter of the Shot will ſuffice; as for the Wheels they muſt be ſtrong, and their height for Land-Service about half the length of the Piece, but on Shipboard lower Carriages are in uſe, the Turneons or bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of the Piece muſt be laid on equal heights upon the turning Irons of the Stock, that the Piece may ſtand true mounted, leaſt ſwerving to any ſide the Shot become Ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and in this caſe two thirds of the Piece muſt appear above their Centre, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Cordage ever ready to move or turn
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:64196:78"/> them, eſpecially for braces at Sea, for many times a Ship is over-ſet and in danger to be loſt by their breaking looſe through the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect of Tackle.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Further Inſtructions neceſſary to be known.</head>
               <p>EVer obſerve that your Budg-Barrel, Leather Bag, or Cartridges of Powder lie on the windy ſide of you, leaſt a ſpark flying from your Match blow it up, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a Diſcharge having cleanſed the Concave with your Sheeps-Skin, Furbiſher, fill your Ladle, but not ſo full as to ſcatter any, and having Charged it as home into the Piece as you can, give it a ſudden turn with your Thumb and Finger, keeping your Body for your own ſafety clear of the Muzzle, and ſo quickly drawing it out, clap in your Wad, and force it down, that the Powder may not lie hollow in the Chamber, then put the Shot in and wad it down, having the Touch-hole all this while covered, leaſt any ſpark ſhould fall in, then having a Linſtock well armed with a good Match and Coale, prime with ſmall Powder, drawing a Train from the Touch-hole, and fire one end of it, for
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:64196:78"/> if you ſhould hold your Match upon the Touch-hole, the force of the Powder would blow it away.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Directions for Shooting at Random, or at a Mark.</head>
               <p>IF your buſineſs lies to ſhoot at Random, or at a Mark, then you are to conſider the Random of a Piece is its entire diſtance from the place where you diſcharge, to the place where the Bullet firſt lights or grazes o a level Line, called a Horizential plain, and to gain the true knowledge of this, the ground muſt be level where it is put in practice, ſo that the level of the ſhot may not be hindred, and having taken notice of the diſtance of ground from the Piece to the fall of the Bullet, mount the Muzzle a degree higher, obſerving again the ſame notice, by which through many degrees you will be capable of knowing, upon the level or Aſcendant, how many paces the Piece will carry with more or leſs Powder, which may be raiſed even to a tenth degree, or as high as the Piece can be mounted, ſo theſe diſtances well underſtood, the Gunner may know how to direct his Piece
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:64196:79"/> either at a Baſtion, Caſtle-Wall, Curtain, Ravelin Counterſcarp againſt the Batteries of Beſiegers, or into their Trenches, or he may batter the Ranks of an Army at a great di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, and many other things incident to true Rules of Fireing even to the ſtriking a Ship under Sail, but in fireing at any thing in Motion, you muſt conſider the ſwiftneſs of it, and Fire in your aim a diſtance before, and ſo the Bullet by that it moves that ſpace will be there, for although a Bullet is carried with great impetuoſity, yet all Motions require time more or leſs.</p>
               <p>If you would ſtrike down a Light in the Stern of a Ship, or in a Caſtle if it be in the Night time, you muſt ſtick directly on the top of the Muzzle of your Piece, either a peice of Wax-Candle lighted, or a fired Match, by which means you will bring that and the other Light together, ſo as to take a fair Mark, and to know whether they are brought together, ſtick up a Nail with a peice of Wax or Clay on the breach of the Pice, and bring that and the other two to bear with each other.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="151" facs="tcp:64196:79"/>
               <head>How to take out a Shot that sticks in a Piece, and cool her to make her recover her Force.</head>
               <p>IT many times happens through too much haſtineſs, or that a Shot is miſtaken, or that the Powder, for want of being rammed down, makes it ſtick half way, ſo that it is dangerous to diſcharge it, without breaking the Piece; in this Caſe let it deſcend, low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ering its Muzzle, and then having diſſolved Bay Salt, or other Salt, in ſome Vinegar put it into the Touch-hole with a Funnel, and it will diſſolve the Powder; then ſtrike on the Piece with a Hand-ſpike where the Bullet lyes, and it will rowl out, having be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore given it a thruſt or two with the Ram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer to looſen it.</p>
               <p>It is taken notice on by all Gunners that the oftner a Piece is diſcharged, it by grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing hot, looſes more, and of it's force, and will not carry the third or fourth time ſo far as it will the firſt or ſecond, every time aba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting ſomewhat, ſo that you muſt cool it, which is much the better done with Vinegar; for that not only carries off the heat, but by the ſharpneſs of it's Quality recovers the loſt force.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="152" facs="tcp:64196:80"/>
               <head>What Powder is made on, and how to try its Goodneſs.</head>
               <p>POwder, a fatal inſtrument of Death, and almoſt of incredible Force, was firſt found by one <hi>Bartholdus Swart</hi> a Monk, by a ſpark of Fire accidentially falling amongſt ſome of his Chimical Preparations, but ſince as to its Force, has been much improved, it is made of the Quinteſſence of Salt-peter, Brimſtone, and Coal Duſt, by grinding and other means, however in long lying after it is made, it will looſe much of its Force, the ſtrength of the of the Salt-Peter, tending downwards, and that of the other matters upwards, and the firſt thing to know whether it be good or not, is to handle it, and obſerve whether it be well dried and corned, this being noted, lay a few Corns ſcattering upon a ſheet of white Paper, and ſet Fire to them, when if ſo it happens, there is a black Mark, or ſindge with a noiſom ſmell left behind, then the Powder is not good, but if there be little or no Mark, or a clear blewiſh Mark, then con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude it fit for Service, but noughty Powder may be made up again, and ſtrengthned with Salt-Peter.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="153" facs="tcp:64196:80"/>
               <head>How to Charge a Mine, blow up a Houſe, to prevent the Progreſs of Fire, or a Ship that is Sunk.</head>
               <p n="1">1. MInes are various, ſome already advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tageous by Vaults, others muſt be carried on under Ground, great difficulties being met withal, as Rock or Springs of Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, however the Mine being made, if there be any conſiderable quantity of Water, the Mines for drineſs of the Powder ought to be Charged with Barrels of Powder, whereas thoſe that are drier may be Charged with Bags or Sacks, the Train may be laid by Match, and ſix Inches of good Match will burn an hour, but if it be for quick Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, a Train may be laid into ſome Trench through Cain Troughs or upon Boards, and great Care muſt be taken that it be ſo Charged, that it refund not, or burſt out upon thoſe that ſpring it.</p>
               <p n="2">2. To take a Houſe directly up, that it ſhall fall directly, as we may ſay in the place where it ſtood, though ſhattered to pieces, place the Powder, if there be any Cellers di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly under the main Beam, lay a Train up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Boards from the Bung-hole of the Barrel, covering it to prevent Sparks falling in the
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:64196:81"/> Train, and place at the head of the Train a peice of Wild-fire, when having given no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice by beat of Drum, ſet Fire to that with your lighted Match at the end of a Linſtock, and retire to a coverture for fear of any ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering Tiles or Timber, if you would throw it ſideways from the Fire, you muſt place the Powder near the contrary ſide under the moſt ſubſtantial Beam, and it will caſt it as you wiſh, ſo that the Timber may be drawn a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way without danger.</p>
               <p>Many times it happens that a Ship ſinks in a River or Channel, and is not worth weighing, yet obſtructs the paſſage, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally at low Water, here you muſt ſend down a Diver to find the entrence in the hold of the Ship. and that found, fix a Leather Pipe with Pitch or Roſin into the Bung of the Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel of Powder, that the end of the Pipe may be above Water when the Barrel is in the Hold which muſt be ſunk and guided down by Cords, then the top of the Pipe ſloating by help of Bladders, the Boat that waits muſt with a long pair of Tongues put a hot Iron Bolt down it, and make of as faſt as may be, elſe the Powder taking Fire, the Wreck will float and endanger the over-ſetting it, or this may be done with a long hollow Fiſhing Cane.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="155" facs="tcp:64196:81"/>
               <head>Fire-works for War, uſed on ſundry occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, the manner of making and uſing them.</head>
               <p>MOſt Fire-works uſed in Sieges are of late thrown out of Mortars, the beſt Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars being made of Braſs or Copper, though ſometimes they have been made of Paſt-board and Wood.</p>
               <p>If the Bore of a Mortar happen to be ten Inches in Diamiter, it ought to be a Foot and nine Inches in length, and the Chamber three Inches and a half in Diamiter, and in depth five Inches, the Mettal above the Port, Fire, to be three Inches and a half in thickneſs, and ſo leſſening to two Inches; as for the plant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing theſe Mortas, the ways are not difficult, for they are moſtly played Mounting, yet the Engenieer ought to be well skilled to direct a Granado Shell to any particular place, for upon his delivering it, he ought to know juſtly where it will fall; likewiſe his Fuzes muſt be ſo exactly made, that they will not break till they are in the place deſigned for Execution.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="156" facs="tcp:64196:82"/>
               <head>How to make, or Order a Granado.</head>
               <p>A Granado is firſt properly called, ſo in relation to its Shell, for the Shell to contain the matter are caſt with hollow ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veties, and a ſmall vent frequently of Iron, but ſome times Braſs, Copper, Glaſs, and Earth, theſe, if deſigned to blow up, or beat down, are uſually filled with dry Powder, and an Iron hollowed or Piſtol Barrel ram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med with Wild-fire made of Brimſtone Flower, Duſt of Powder, Salt-peter, and Oyl of Petrolum drove into the Vent of the filled Shell to an Inch, when the Mortar being Charged, the Granado muſt be ſlung in with Ropes put in the Hooks of the Shell if it be very great, then having taken your Aim, you muſt a minute before you give Fire, Fire the Fuze, then by Fireing the Mortar, ſend it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way to the place deſigned; and of ſuch dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly force is this Engine of Miſchief, that fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling upon a Caſtle, Church, or Houſe, it breaks through to the lowermoſt Flore, beat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing down all before it, and then blows up and rends in a terrible manner, the Shell break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in a thouſand peices.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
